<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The marriage of the lambe Or a treatise concerning the spirituall espousing of Christ, to a beleeving soule, wherein the subject is fully handled in the nature of it, in the effects, priviledges, symptomes, with the comforts that arise to a beleever from this relation, wherein also the excellencie of Christ, and many other spirituall truths flowing from the subject are by way discovered. By Benjamin King, minister of Gods Word at Flamsteed in Hartford-shire.</title>
            <author>King, Benjamin, b. 1611 or 12.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839111</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839111</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1245:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The marriage of the lambe Or a treatise concerning the spirituall espousing of Christ, to a beleeving soule, wherein the subject is fully handled in the nature of it, in the effects, priviledges, symptomes, with the comforts that arise to a beleever from this relation, wherein also the excellencie of Christ, and many other spirituall truths flowing from the subject are by way discovered. By Benjamin King, minister of Gods Word at Flamsteed in Hartford-shire.</title>
                  <author>King, Benjamin, b. 1611 or 12.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 167, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Cotes for R. H[arper?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MARRIAGE OF THE LAMBE. OR A Treatiſe concerning the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eſpouſing of Chriſt, to a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving Soule, wherein the ſubject is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled in the nature of it, in the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, priviledges, ſymptomes, with the comforts that ariſe to a beleever from this relation, wherein alſo the excellencie of Chriſt, and many other ſpirituall truths flowing from the ſubject are by way diſcovered.</p>
            <p>By BENIAMIN KING, Miniſter of Gods Word at <hi>Flamſteed</hi> in <hi>Hartford</hi>-ſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 21.9.</hi>
               </bibl> Come hither, I will ſhew thee the Bride, the Lambes Wife.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>R.H.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:2"/>
            <head>TO The Right Worſhipfull, truly Worthy, and very much honoured Knight and Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Barrington,</hi> and to his truely vertuous Lady, Grace, Mercy, and Peace from the Fountaine.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any are thoſe Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that Chriſt the Prince of Peace ſtands in towards beleevers, He a Father, they his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he a Sheapheard, they
<pb facs="tcp:3510:3"/>
his ſheepe, he an head, they his members, he a King, they his Subjects, he a Lord, they his Servants, he a generall, they his Souldiers, he an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, they his ſpouſe; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all theſe relations, not one enricheth the beleeving heart with more heavenly conſolation than this, of being a husband to his Church, for by this the beleever becomes aſſured of all things his heart can deſire, of Communion with Chriſt, of protection, preſervation, maintenance, ſpirituall and temporall, yea of heaven it ſelfe Chriſts
<pb facs="tcp:3510:3"/>
ſpouſes joynture: of this moſt comfortable ſubject I have publiſhed this ſmall treatiſe, and the cauſe inforcing mee to the publication thereof, was the earneſt requeſt of ſome speciall and neere friends, whoſe affections were much moved with the Subject handled in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit: to ſatisfie their deſire (being no leſſe to me than a command) and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Edification of Gods Church, I have endeavoured to publiſh the notes ſomewhat more fully handled than in the Pulpit, hoping that none
<pb facs="tcp:3510:4"/>
will deſpiſe <hi>Timothie</hi> for his Youth, conſidering that out of the mouth of Babes the praiſe of God is perfected. Although I want not ſome private respects to inforce me to dedicate this my labour unto your Worſhips, as that I may give ſome open teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my gratefull minde to you both, for thoſe perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall favoure received, yet the chiefeſt reaſon was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Treatiſe ſeemes to be due to you both, who are joyned together not onely in the common bonds of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, but as <hi>Aquila</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:3510:4"/>
               <hi>Priſcylla, Zacharie</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> married together in the Lord and to the Lord Jeſus, as to one Husband: this relation to Jeſus Chriſt appeares by that high reſpect you ſhew to the ſpokeſmen and faithfull miniſters of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by your Pietie and Zeale for the honour of the Lord Ieſus. Let <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> contend for ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority in fading and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing greatneſse. Let your Worſhips contend with an holy ambition for the obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and retaining of Gods favour, and an humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance
<pb facs="tcp:3510:5"/>
and communion with his heavenly highneſſe, by <hi>keeping Faith and a pure Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the men of this world, whoſe ſole portion is in this life, glory that they are crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a concurrance of preſent felicities. Let your Worſhips glory be, that toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a confluence of worldly contentments, the God of heaven hath crowned you with his Mercy and Grace in Chriſt, and eſteeme it your chiefeſt Honour that God hath made you Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable with the <hi>Bereans</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:3510:5"/>
your love to the truth; with <hi>Iabez</hi> for your Piety and Devotion, and that he hath made you Noble with <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi> for your love to God, his People, his Lawes, his Cauſe, which love of truth, piety, and devotion; love to God and his cauſe, ſhall give a luster to all your other greatneſse, and ſhall be able in the day of tryall and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to make you ſtand like an unmoveable Rocke with triumphing confidence before the terrour of the last day, when all other worldly great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes without the former ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:3510:6"/>
ſhrinke in the wetting, and ſhall wiſh it ſelfe ſo little it could not be ſeene; in that ſhall call to the Mountaines to fall upon it and to cover it. The great God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, repleniſh your Noble hearts with a dayly increaſe of heavenly hords of Grace, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Comforts in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Holineſſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in well doing, which may give you an earnest of thoſe inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable treaſures of joy and happineſſe, reſerved in the highest heavens for
<pb facs="tcp:3510:6"/>
all that love the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in ſincerity, this ſhall be the dayly prayer of him who humbly deſires to bee accounted</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friend and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant for the good of your Soules: BENIAMIN KING.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3510:7"/>
            <head>THE MARRIAGE OF THE LAMBE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hoſea 2.20.</hi>
                  </bibl> I will betroth thee unto me in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſweeteſt mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſique conſiſts of diſcords. It is ſo with the Harmonie of Gods Word in generall, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3510:8"/>
with this Chapter in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. In the former part to the 12. <hi>verſe,</hi> God ſtands as it were upon Mount <hi>Eball</hi> pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing his curſes; from the 12. <hi>verſe</hi> to the end, he ſtands as it were upon Mount <hi>Gerizim</hi> proclaiming his mercies; in the former as upon Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> thundring in his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in the latter part as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> alluring in many ſweete and Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call promiſes, of which his text is the ſummary and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the reſt. <hi>I will betroth thee unto me in faithfulneſſe.</hi> The matter included in this text is this.</p>
            <p>That there is a ſpirituall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothing of Chriſt unto every truely beleeving ſoule, which will more fully appeare, if we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3510:8"/>
conſider theſe three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p>Firſt the precedent of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſpirituall Marriage.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the nature and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> eſſence of it, or the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars wherein it conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Conſequents of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it.</p>
            <p>The precedent of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Marriage, which is this; that before Chriſt vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth to eſpouſe himſelf to any ſoule, there muſt be a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt that ſoule and every beloved ſinne; as the woman muſt bury her former husband before ſhee can be marryed to another: ſo the Soule muſt bury all former beloved ſinnes, that it may be betrothed to Chriſt. Every
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3510:9"/>
Chriſtian before the act of this ſpirituall betrothing is wedded to one ſinne or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, which walkes with him in the day, ſleepes with him in the night, that lyes in his boſome, and is as deare to him as his wife, but before Chriſt eſpouſeth himſelfe unto that ſoule, there muſt be a bill of divorcement drawne betwixt it, and all other dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſinnes, and endeared cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions to give entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Chriſt alone. The Harlot could be content the living childe ſhould be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.26. whereas the true mother of the childe had rather part with all the childe, than to have the childe divided. The Devill like the Harlot can be content to have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3510:9"/>
halfe the heart, becauſe hee knowes, if hee hath halfe the heart, by this meanes hee ſhall enjoy the whole; but Chriſt like the true mother of the Childe, will have all or none, though a broken heart be his delight, yet a divided heart is odious unto him, hence is it that Chriſt before he vouchſafeth this favour of eſpouſing himſelfe to any ſoule, requires there ſhould be a divorcement of all ſinne to give entertainement to himſelfe alone, this is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 45.11.12. <hi>Hearken O daughter and conſider, incline thine eare: forget alſo thine owne people, and thy Fathers houſe. So ſhall the King have pleaſure in thy beauty, for he is thy Lord God, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3510:10"/>
thou him:</hi> Our Prophet, <hi>v.</hi> 16. of this chapter, ſhewes the truth of this, that Chriſt in his love will permit no corrivall: Thou ſhalt call me <hi>Iſhi</hi> and call me no more <hi>Bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cornel. de Lap. in <hi>Hoſ. 2.16</hi> Par. in eundem locum.</note> why not <hi>Bauli</hi> as well as <hi>Iſhi?</hi> they ſignifying both the ſame thing, ſounding as much as <hi>my Lord, my husband:</hi> the reaſon was becauſe <hi>Baal</hi> was the name of an Idoll, now God doth ſo abhorre that an Idoll ſhould have the leaſt communication and corriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with him, that hee would not be called by the name of an Idoll, ſo offenſive is the very name of another lover unto him. So <hi>Hoſea</hi> 14.8. <hi>Ephraim</hi> being once eſpouſed to God, cryes out, <hi>what have I to doe any more with Idols:</hi> ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3510:10"/>
the Apoſtle perſwading the <hi>Romans</hi> to put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, hee bids them firſt to abjure <hi>ſurfetting and drunkennes, chanbering and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe, and ſo to put on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the nature and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> eſſence of this ſpirituall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, and the particulars wherein it doth conſiſt, which are three. Firſt in that neere <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and intimate conjunction, that is betwixt Chriſt and every beleeving ſoule, which is ſo great and intimate, that Chriſt and a beleever are ſayd to bee one: <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.32. <hi>they two ſhall be one fleſh, this is a great myſtery, but I ſpeake of Chriſt and his Church,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. Now this union is not a meere notionall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3510:11"/>
union, that conſiſts only in the underſtanding, and without the underſtanding is nothing, nor yet a conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of affection onely, as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> are ſayd to have one ſoule and heart, but it is a true and reall union; nor yet ſuch a reall union as if there was an union of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and perſon, for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny beleevers there are, ſo many diſtinct perſons there are, and all diſtinct from the perſon of Chriſt and his God-head, which is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municable; but this union is a reall, myſticall, and ſpirituall union, cauſed two wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt in regard of Chriſt by his ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in regard of us by a true, vivificall, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3510:11"/>
faith.</p>
            <p>Firſt on Chriſts part, by his <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Spirit, for as in the members of the body they are all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct amongſt themſelves, and doe all differ from the head, yet <hi>ab unâ eadémque for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ informante,</hi> from one and the ſame ſoule informing the head and all the members, all they are made one <hi>compoſitum.</hi> So it is with Chriſt and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers: beleevers are diſtinct perſons and diſtinct from the perſon of Chriſt, yet by one and the ſame Spirit, abiding in Chriſt and beleevers they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one, this the Apoſtle intimates, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>He that is joyned to the Lord is one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> that Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that leaned on Chriſts breaſts, and thence ſuckt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3510:12"/>
a ſpiritual truth, makes the participation of the Spirit an evidence of Chriſts abiding in beleevers, and of their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in Chriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.24.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, this union is cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on beleevers part by the grace of faith, ſo ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>I will betroth thee unto me in faithfulneſſe,</hi> ſome would have this word <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to God, and ſo to note the truth of Gods promiſe of eſpouſing himſelfe unto his Church, but others better take this word <hi>faithfulneſſe,</hi> to note the grace of juſtifying faith; for I finde the word here uſed in the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be referred to the ſaving faith of the juſt, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.4. <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his owne faith,</hi> ſo that the meaning of the Prophet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3510:12"/>
in this place is this: whereas <hi>verſe</hi> 19. he ſaith in regard of God, this eſpouſing is in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy, ſo on belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers part, it muſt bee in faith and obedience, ſo that it is faith which is the applicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtrument of this great benefit of this ſpirituall Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; for God will ſo eſpouſe himſelfe in juſtice and mercy, as that the beleever muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive this grace by faith.</p>
            <p>This ſpirituall betrothing <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> conſiſts in that mutuall cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that is made betwixt Chriſt and a beleever, in the day of their eſpouſalls, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. <hi>I entred into covenant with thee,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and thou becameſt mine,</hi> which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is that Chriſt will bee to the ſoule a loving and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3510:13"/>
husband, and the ſoule muſt be to Chriſt a morige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and an obedient ſpouſe, this mutuall covenant the Apoſtle expreſſeth fully, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.24.25, <hi>Husbands love your wives, as Chriſt loved his Church,</hi> there is the covenant on Chriſts part: <hi>Wives be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to your husbands as the Church is ſubject unto Chriſt;</hi> there is the covenant on the beleevers part: this covenant is expreſſed by this Prophet, <hi>verſe</hi> laſt: <hi>I will be your God and ye my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> It conſiſts in that recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call intereſt that Chriſt claimes in a beleever and a beleever in Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16. <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his: my beloved is mine,</hi> there is the beleevers intereſt in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3510:13"/>
Chriſt, <hi>and I am his,</hi> there is Chriſts intereſt in a beleever. A beleever doth not by faith ſo lay hold on Chriſt as a man with his hand layes hold on a Pillar or tree, for a man may lay hold on a tree, and the tree never lay hold on him againe; but he layes hold on Chriſt ſo by faith, that by the ſame act of faith he is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by Chriſt againe: this the Apoſtle intimates, <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p.</hi> 3.13. <hi>I follow after, if that I may apprehend that for which alſo I am apprehended of Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> here is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> an apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and a being apprehended of Chriſt, and therefore this mutuall apprehending of a beleever by Chriſt, and of Chriſt by a beleever, is lively
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3510:14"/>
expreſſed by the metaphor of kiſſing and ſaluting, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his lippes;</hi> here the Church would have Chriſt to kiſſe her. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>ult. Kiſſe the Sonne:</hi> here Chriſt deſires a kiſſe of his Church; in this ſaluting and kiſſing, there is a mutuall embracing and touching of one another, this expreſſeth the manner of the worke of faith in apprehending Chriſt, for by faith the ſoule ſo em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth Chriſt that by the ſame Act of faith it is embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Chriſt againe, this is that mutuall intereſt as the beleeving ſoule challengeth Chriſt to be its Bridſgroome, ſo it gives Chriſt an intereſt in it ſelfe to bee his faithfull and obedient ſpouſe, and this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3510:14"/>
diſtinguiſheth the falſ ſpouſe of Chriſt from the true ſpouſe: there is never an hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite and nominall Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that hath no more of Chriſtianity than the outſide and title, but he will be ready to claime intereſt in Chriſt; crying I hope in my God, my Chriſt, my Jeſus; but the queſtion is, whether Chriſt hath intereſt in him, if not, his claiming of intereſt in Chriſt will availe him nothing. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22.23. <hi>Many will ſay to</hi> Chriſt at the laſt <hi>day; Lord, Lord, we have Propheſied in thy Name, we have in thy Name caſt out Devils, and done many won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes:</hi> here is a faire intereſt in Chriſt pretended, but Chriſt diſclaimes them as having no intereſt in them:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3510:15"/>
               <hi>I never knew you, depart from me ye workers of iniquity.</hi> But it is otherwiſe with the true Chriſtian and ſincere belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: as he is able to ſay that Chriſt is his Saviour, Lord, and Brideſgroome, ſo is he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to affirme by the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his Conſcience, that Chriſt hath intereſt in him as his obedient ſervant and faithfull ſpouſe, thus we ſee the particulars, wherein this ſpirituall Marriage doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> This ſpirituall Marriage will further appeare, if in the third place wee conſider the conſequents of this ſpirituall eſpouſing. The conſequents <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> are of two kindes. Firſt, ſome are mutuall and reciprocall betwixt Chriſt and beleevers.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3510:15"/>
Secondly, ſome are proper <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and peculiar either to Chriſt, or to his Church and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. 1. the mutuall and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> conſequents betwixt Chriſt and beleevers are theſe. The firſt is that mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> delight and content that Chriſt takes in his Spouſe, and his Spouſe in Chriſt. This the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> expreſſeth on Gods part that his people ſhould be called <hi>Hephzibah,</hi> that is, my delight is in her: and thy land <hi>Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah,</hi> that is, married, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that as the Bridſgroome rejoyceth over his Bride; ſo the Lord would rejoyce over his people: this delight is ſo great that Chriſt takes in his Spouſe, that Chriſt affirmes hee was raviſhed in his heart
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3510:16"/>
by his Spouſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.9. and acknowledgeth himſelfe to bee bound in her galleries. <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.5. That is tyed in bonds of love towards his Spouſe: and as Chriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights thus in his Spouſe, ſo the ſatisfied ſoule delights in Chriſt, and that many wayes. Firſt in the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of his perſon, his beauty and comelineſſe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10. <hi>My beloved is white and ruddy, the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Chriſts Spouſe delights in his preſence. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.3. <hi>I ſate down under his ſhadow with great delight, and his fruite was ſweete to my taſte.</hi> So <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> makes this his chiefe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and his onely deſire to dwell in the houſe of God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. and this he deſires
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3510:16"/>
that he may behold the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Lord. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chriſts ſpouſe delights in hearing her bridſgroomes voyce. <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8. <hi>It is the voyce of my beloved.</hi> This is the Churches acclamation for joy at the hearing of Chriſts voyce, the word of Grace and the Goſpell. Chriſt gives this as an eare-marke to his ſheepe; <hi>My ſheepe heare my voyce, and follow me, Iohn</hi> 10.3.4. and the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> makes this a ſigne of a friend to the Bridſgroome that hee ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth by and rejoyceth great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe of the Brideſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes voyce. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.29. Fourthly, Chriſts Spouſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> in his Lawes: <hi>His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) is in the Law of God,</hi> ſpeaking of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3510:17"/>
bleſſed man. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Thy Lawes are my delight, my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, ſweeter than the Honey and the Honey combe, dearer than thouſands of gold and ſilver. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Pſal.</hi> 119. Laſtly a beleever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in communing with Chriſt and ſpeaking unto him in prayer: heare what ſweete expreſſions have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a ſanctifyed ſoule. <hi>Lord I have loved the habitation of thine houſe: I was glad when they ſayd, let us goe to the houſe of the Lord, which is the houſe of prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond conſequent of this ſpirituall marriage that is mutual betwixt Chriſt and his ſpouſe, is cohabitation,<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. Eth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> a co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>habitation is neceſſary to the making &amp; conſerving of true friendſhip, much more to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3510:17"/>
preſervation of conjugall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, therefore<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Oeconomic. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> thinketh nothing to be more due to bee performed of an husband to his wiſe, than an holy ſociety: this bleſſed ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie is maintained betwixt Chriſt and his ſpouſe, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.4. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in me, and I in you,</hi> and by his Diſciple whom he loved. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. <hi>ult. He that keepeth his Commandements dwelleth in him, and he in him.</hi> This ſociety is performed on Chriſts part when hee is preſent by his ſpirit in the Temple of the beleevers heart, confirming, comforting, and refreſhing of him by his ſpirit, in the aſſurance of his love, ſo Chriſt told his Diſciples he would not leave them Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3510:18"/>
but he would come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them and be with them to the end of the world, though not in his perſonall preſence, yet by the Comforter his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit; againe this mutuall ſociety is performed on the ſoules part with Chriſt, whilſt the ſoule with <hi>Henoch</hi> and <hi>Noah</hi> walkes with God, having God alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its eyes, alwayes aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an apprehenſion of his glorious preſence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming it ſelfe to his will in all things, often hearing him ſpeake in his houſe, often ſpeaking unto him by prayer, often frequenting his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, often communing with holy meditations, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly ſoliloquies and ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, this is the ſecond
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3510:18"/>
conſequent.</p>
            <p>A third conſequent mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all betwixt Chriſt and a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leever, is a mutuall bearing of one anothers burden,<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomicae. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n principio.</note> A good husband ſaith the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, undertakes the care of things abroad, a good wife undergoes the burden of domeſticke affaires and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to bee done within doores, and thus hath the wiſe diſpoſer of all things appointed man and wife their ſeverall employments agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their ſeverall ſexes and diſtinct conditions. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſpeaking of the wife, ſaith that ſhe ſhould be <hi>as the pleaſant Hind and young Roe,</hi> now, as<note n="(d)" place="margin">Cervi &amp; Cervae cum fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam tranſeunt paſcuorum gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ſic ſe ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ut onera capitum ſuorum quae geſtant in cornibus ſuper invicem por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, ita ut po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterior ſuper anteriorum cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice projecta, caput collocet, &amp; vicibus id agere dicuntur, ita invicem onera ſua portantes fretum tranſeunt ad terrae ſtabilitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Aug. q.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> notes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3510:19"/>
the Hart and Hinde are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, one to another in bearing one anothers burden. It is ſo with Chriſt and his Church, he takes the burden off his Spouſe, and layes it upon himſelfe, and gives his Spouſe a command to take upon her his yoke. <hi>Math.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Come unto me all yee that are weary and heavie laden, and I will eaſe you,</hi> here Chriſt bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the yoke of his ſpouſe, <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>Take my yoke upon you,</hi> here Chriſt enjoyneth his ſpouſe to take up his yoke as he hath borne here; the yoke that Chriſt beareth for his ſpouſe, is the yoke of ſinne, and the burden of Gods wrath under which all the creatures in heaven, and upon earth, would have ſunke downe to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3510:19"/>
have undergone, therefore Chriſt both God and man undertakes to beare it for his ſpouſe, and the burden and yoke that Chriſt impoſeth on his ſpouſe to beare is the yoke of obedience, called Chriſts yoke, becauſe he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath borne it, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe enjoynes it,<note n="(e)" place="margin">Is dat qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandat, qui ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, illo juvat.</note> and hee himſelfe ſupports his ſpouſe in bearing of it, this yoke of Chriſt doth his ſpouſe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly beare in performing univerſall, cheerefull, ſincere and conſtant obedience to all Chriſts commands in full purpoſe and deſire of the heart, in the earneſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the whole man, which Evangelicall obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence Chriſt accepts and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts as perfect obedience
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3510:20"/>
for his owne ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth conſequent of this ſpirituall marriage of Chriſt and his Spouſe, is that mutuall adhaering and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> cleaving to one another in ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of<note n="(f)" place="margin">Quam quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris aliam inter ſponſos neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem, vel connexionem praeten amari &amp; amare. <hi>Bern. Ser.</hi> 31. <hi>in Cant.</hi>
               </note> affection and deareſt love. Firſt, for the love of Chriſt to a beleever it is tranſcendent, and differing from a Chriſtians love to Chriſt. Firſt in time: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in degree: thirdly as a cauſe differs from an effect. Firſt in time, Chriſts love is the preventing love, and this magnifies the love of Chriſt; it is a chiefe porperty of great love when it is<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Rhet. c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> preventing and therefore the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> calls it love indeede that <hi>Chriſt loved us firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſts love dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3510:20"/>
and exceedes the love of his Spouſe in degree, he being the fountaine of love, and the love of a Chriſtian but a ſtreame flowing from that fountaine, hee the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2. From whom the beames of mercies flow dayly upon the hearts of his beloved ones; their love being but a beame comming from that Sonne, therefore God is ſayd to bee love it ſelfe in the abſtract, in regard of the tranſcenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his love ſurpaſſing the love of all. Thirdly, Chriſts <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> love differs from a Chriſtians love, as the cauſe differs from the effect for the love of a Chriſtian to Chriſt is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an heavenly ſparke kindled by the fire of Gods
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3510:21"/>
Spirit and the fervencie of his affection to a Chriſtian: the heate that is in the inferiour region of the ayre, is nothing but an effect of the reverbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the beames of the Sunne upon the earth, the heate of a Chriſtians heart that burnes within him, with a love and zeale to the Lord Jeſus, is nothing elſe but a reflection of thoſe hot ſunne beames of Chriſts mercies ſhed abroad in the heart of a beleever. Our cloathes in the morning receive heate firſt from our bodies, but being heated by our bodies, they keepe our bodies warme all the day following: A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians heart muſt firſt be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with the ſunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and ſo warmed with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3510:21"/>
his beames, being but once throughly warmed, it ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glowes within towards Chriſt in love againe: now as Chriſt beares a love to a Chriſtian farre exceeding the love of the fondeſt Bridſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome to his endeared Spouſe, ſo there is a retalia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting affection in every belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoule towards Chriſt. We may as well imagine fire without a power to give heate, as to imagine Chriſts love beſtowed upon a ſoule without this affection in the heart, to whom Chriſt hath made his love knowne by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothing himſelfe.<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ariſt. Rhet. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaking of a friend deſcribes him to be ſuch an one that loves and is loved againe: And againe in another place
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3510:22"/>
affirmes that to bee true friendſhip where love is<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> magni. moral. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> reciprocall, if then love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt friends be mutuall much more betwixt<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Oeconomie. c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> man and wife, betwixt Chriſt and his Spouſe, the very name of Bridſgroome calls for love.<note n="(l)" place="margin">Ludolphus de vita Chriſti ex Gregorio.</note> It is the obſervation of a Father, ſometimes God calls himſelfe by the name of a Father, ſometimes by the name of a Maſter, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by the name of a Bridſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, when he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a filiall feare in the hearts of his children, hee calls himſelfe by the name of a Father. If I be a Father where is my feare? when he would produce homage and ſervice in his ſervants hee calls himſelfe by the name
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3510:22"/>
of a Lord. If I bee your Maſter and Lord, where is me honour and ſervice? When hee would beget love and affection in them hee ſtiles himſelfe a Bridſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome. If I bee a Bridſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome where is my love? Now this love that a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian oweth and giveth to Chriſt as the Spouſe of Chriſt, hath ſeverall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct properties, whereby it is diſcerned from the love that worldlings may pretend to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is ſuch a love <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that will drive the ſoule to ſickneſſe in caſe the thing loved bee delayed. <hi>Conticles cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>I am ſicke of love,</hi> ſaith the Church concerning Chriſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3510:23"/>
her Bridſgrome: this ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſoule for love is nothing but a fainting and languiſhing for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Chriſt, whom the ſoule loveth, this the wiſe man expreſſeth, <hi>Pro.</hi> 13.12. <hi>Hope deferred, maketh the heart ſicke,</hi> now the ſoule hoping for thoſe ſoule-tranſporting plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to bee found in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Chriſts favour and ſenſe of his preſence, and yet obtaines not the inward apprehenſion of his gracious reſidence in the ſoule, upon this the heart begins to faint and languiſh, and to bee ſicke of love: the deſire of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian towards Chriſt is not any faint and remiſſe deſire, but a longing deſire, ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that ſtretcheth the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3510:23"/>
to the higheſt ſtraine, and therefore expreſſed in Scripture by the metaphors of thirſting, gaſping, panting, now as experience teacheth in ſome caſes, longing brings danger when the thing lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for is not obtained; whereas an ordinary deſire will not hurt in the deniall of the thing deſired: as the effects of longing are dangerous when the thing longed for is delayed, as fainting, ſownding, languiſhing, it is ſo in ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall longing for Chriſt, the ſoule thirſting for Chriſt, and finding him not, falls a ſownding, fainting and grows to a kinde of Sprituall ſickneſſe for love and deſire of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>This love is a kinde of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3510:24"/>
love that carries the ſoule to a ſpirituall diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this we may ſee in <hi>Peter,</hi> who in the transfigration was ſo tranſported with affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo raviſhed with the love of Chriſt, that like a man ſpiritually diſtracted he knew not what hee ſayd, ſaith the text, <hi>Marke 9.6.</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in his rapture into the third heaven, he ſpeakes like a man beſides himſelfe for the preſent. 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12.2.3. <hi>and</hi> 5. <hi>I knew a man in Chriſt above foureteene yeares agoe, whether in the body I cannot tell, or whether out of the body I cannot tell; God knoweth: ſuch an one caught up to the third heaven: and I knew ſuch a man, whether in the body, or out of the body I cannot
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3510:24"/>
tell, God knoweth.</hi> verſe 5. <hi>Of ſuch an one will I glory, of my ſelfe I will not glory:</hi> here wee ſee the Apoſtle for the preſent in a bleſſed kinde of ſpirituall diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in love to Chriſt, and heaven, whereunto hee was caught.</p>
            <p>This love in the third place is a<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <p>Amat pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto caſtè quae ipſum, quem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat, quaerit, non aliud quid praeter ipſum. <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 7. <hi>in Canti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sponſa non pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit libertatem, non mercedem, non haeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſed oſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum more pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè caſtiſſimae ſponſae, ac ſacrum ſpirantis amorem, nec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omnino valen tis flammam diſſimulare, quam patitur, oſculetur, inquit, me oſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo oris ſui, quaſi dicat, quid mihi eſt in coelo, &amp; a te quid volui ſuper terram. <hi>Bern. ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> free love whereby the beleeving ſoule cleaves unto Chriſt for himſelfe and thoſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous excellencies it ſees in our Saviour Chriſt, this property diſtinguiſheth it from that<note n="(n)" place="margin">Cave anima, ne, quod abſit, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrix dicaris, ſi munera dantis plus quam amantis affectum diligis. <hi>Aug. medit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> meretritious
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3510:25"/>
and mercenary love in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, that follow Chriſt as Chriſt upbraided ſome of the ſame ſtampe for the fiſhes and bread wherewith hee fed them. <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.26. This hired love the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Cum magno calumniatore habemus nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, ſi quaerit ſingere quod non eſt, ut in Iob. quanto magis objicere quod eſt? <hi>Aug. de temp. Serm.</hi> 234.</note> Devils objected againſt <hi>Iobs</hi> ſincerity; <hi>Doth Iob feare God for nought?</hi> but <hi>Iob</hi> cleaving to God upon the dunghill, and in the loweſt condition, proved the Devill in that particular as hee was from the beginning, to be a lyar.</p>
            <p>The fourth property of a Chriſtians love to Chriſt the Bridſgroome of his ſoule is, that it is a ſtrong and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory love; it will carry a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian through all<note n="(p)" place="margin">Amemus nos Chriſtum ejuſque ſemper quaeramus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexus, &amp; facile videbitur omne difficile, brevia putabimus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa quae lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga ſunt. &amp; ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo illius vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerati perho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta dicemus: Heus, me quia pereginatio mea prolonga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta eſt. Hier. ſcribeus ad Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtochium.</note> difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and ſtraights to Chriſt. The love of <hi>Rachel</hi> carried
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3510:25"/>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> through 14. yeares of hard ſervice, the love of Chriſt will carry a Chriſtian through more difficulties than <hi>Labans</hi> ſervice had in it. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6.7. It is ſayd to be as ſtrong as death, that conquers the greateſt gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and the mightieſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch: zeale, that is, love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed is as inexorable as hell it ſelfe, it is ſayd to have fiery coales that pierce the heart, which fiery coales of love all the waters, be it a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge and inundation of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and temptations, are not able to quench. Love is of that ſtrength that it facilitates the greateſt difficulties. This we ſee in the ordinary bodily recreations, many men take a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3510:26"/>
pleaſure in a toyle as in hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, running, leaping, ringing, wraſtling, and the like, and all out of love to theſe recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, much more is the love of Chriſt able to ſweeten the hardeſt duty that Chriſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth upon his Spouſe. What was it that made the fiery faggots to thoſe bleſſed witneſſes of the truth to ſeeme as beds of Roſes? but love. What made the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to forſake all? but Chriſt, and that love they beare to him. What made <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> ſing in Priſon, and the Apoſtles to returne from the Councill rejoycing that they were counted worthy to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for Chriſt? but love to Chriſt. What made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Champion <hi>Stephen</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3510:26"/>
valiant in the midſt of death? but the ſight of the Sonne of God, ſtanding at the right hand of his father, and I am perſwaded that if it had beene offered to <hi>Stephen</hi> that hee ſhould have beene delivered from his preſent paine, upon condition he ſhould have beene deprived of his preſent viſion of Chriſt, by the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the heavens, the love of Chriſt, would not have ſuffered <hi>Stephen</hi> to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of deliverance upon ſuch condition, ſo we reade of thoſe ſtrong ones in faith though weake in ſexe, they would not accept of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the middeſt of their torturings that they might obtaine a better reſurrection. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. To conclude
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3510:27"/>
this, <hi>Paul</hi> being armed with this love challengeth all the powers and peeres of hell it ſelfe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. <hi>Who ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate us from the love of Chriſt, ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſſe, or perſecution, or famine, or naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or perill, or ſword?</hi> as if he had ſayd, ſhall this or that, if there be any more put them all into the ſcale, and weigh but the love of Chriſt againſt them all, and they ſhall bee found too light to ſway my heart from the love of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth property, the love of Chriſts Spouſe is a bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full love, this the Apoſtle. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. makes a proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of true Charity, that it is bountifull:<note n="(q)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. Ethic. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> bounty is the fruite of love, and it is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3510:27"/>
towards any thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to love: if a man love his body, nothing is thought too dainty to feede it, too gorgeous to cloath it; if a man love his pleaſure, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is counted too deare to maintaine it: ſo where there is any true conjugal affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in a Chriſtian heart, that heart will relliſh any thing that tends to the honour of Chriſt, it will downe with frequent prayer, humble and dayly confeſſion of ſinne, zealous and Godly walking with God, ſincere univerſall, and conſtant obedience to Chriſt, though it be with the parting of the moſt dearely beloved ſinnes, that ſoule will thinke no teares of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, no hearing, reading,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3510:28"/>
ſinging, no duties publicke or private too much, whereby the honour of Chriſt may be advanced, and its love to Chriſt better expreſſed. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.47. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> is ſayd to love much, and this her great love was expreſſed to Chriſt, by her bounty in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing his feete, in anointing his head, in wiping his feete with the haires of her head, and Chriſt himſelfe accepts of her waſhing, anointing, kiſſing and all other of her acts of bounty, as Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of her great inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The ſixth property of this love is that it is intire, as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his ſerpent devoured all other ſerpents, becauſe his ſerpent was from God, ſo the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3510:28"/>
love of God being from God eates and conſumes the love of all things beſides, as it is ſayd of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> that there was none greater in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Court, and in the land of <hi>Aegypt</hi> than himſelfe, the like may be ſayd of Chriſt in a beleeving heart, there is none greater than Chriſt, he is the Pilot that governes the ſhip, the King that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes the whole man, the Maſter and Lord that keepes the houſe of a ſanctified heart, to whom, as King and Lord, all the powers of the whole man ſubmit, all doe homage, all performe reſpect, feare, and love, and if there be love beſtowed upon any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing beſides Chriſt, as upon our ſelves and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3510:29"/>
yet it is for Chriſts ſake and in ſubordination to him, whom to love in due meaſure, is to love without meaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> The ſeventh property of a Chriſtians ſoules love to Chriſt is, that it is a conſtant love, it is no great matter to profeſſe love to Chriſt, when nothing comes in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him, but when plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, profit, liberty, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment comes in the way that either a man muſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake theſe or the profeſſion of his love to Chriſt then for to cleave unto Chriſt proves our love to be conjugall. The young man in the Goſpell made many ſhewes of his love to Chriſt, but when Chriſt bad him goe and ſell
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3510:29"/>
all that he had, he went away ſorrowfull. The Rulers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them profeſſed faire love to Chriſt, but yet when it came to this paſſe, that they which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſt muſt be caſt out of the Synagogue,<note place="margin">Iohn 12.42.</note> they would not confeſſe him any longer, ſo that it is conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in our love to Chriſt that proves our love to bee a true conjugall affection. Thus much of the conſequents of this ſpirituall marriage, which are mutuall betwixt Chriſt and his ſpouſe, the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents that are proper and peculiar follow, and theſe are either</p>
            <p>Such as are <hi>exparte ſponſi,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> on Chriſts part.</p>
            <p>Such as ere <hi>ex parte ſponſae,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:3510:30"/>
on a beleevers part.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, ſuch as are on Chriſts <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> part, which are two, 1. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of ſecrets. 2. A communication of goods. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt a communication of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets:<note place="margin">The 1. conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent on Chriſts part.</note> Chriſt will communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thoſe ſecrets to a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoule eſpouſed unto him, that hee will not communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to a ſtranger: a man will communicate much to his friend according to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: All things amongſt friends are common, but much more will a man communicate to the wife of his boſome: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah, Sampſons</hi> wife could get the meaning of the riddle out of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> that all the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> could not finde out: ſo is the Spouſe of Chriſt privie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3510:30"/>
to thoſe ſecrets that all the wiſe and learned, being not eſpouſed to Chriſt, are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of. <hi>The ſecrets of the Lord are to them that feare him. Pſal.</hi> 25.13. <hi>He revealeth his ſecrets to his Servants the Prophets, Amos,</hi> 3.7. <hi>My beloved had me into his Chambers,</hi> ſaith the Spouſe of Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4.<note place="margin">Cant. 1.4. ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> Now as Chambers are places of ſafety, as the Prophet ſheweth, <hi>Iſay</hi> 26.20. <hi>Come my people, enter into my chamber:</hi> ſo chambers are places of greateſt ſecrecie, hence in Scripture they are called pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie chambers, and ſecret pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces oppoſed to the houſe top. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. for Chriſt then to have his Spouſe into his Chambers is nothing elſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3510:31"/>
but to make her privie to his ſecrets, for this priviledge our bleſſed Saviour broke forth into a Doxologie unto his father. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>I thanke thee O Father that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt revealed them unto babes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> What are thoſe ſecrets that Chriſt will communicate to his Spouſe, that hee will not communicate to a ſoule that is not married to him?<note place="margin">Solution.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">Dic nobis tu qui preparas quid preparas: replebiniur bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis domus tuae, ſed quib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis? vine, olco, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umento? ſed haec novimus videmus &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtidimus, id quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus quod o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus non vidit <hi>Bern. Serm.</hi> 11. <hi>in Caniic.</hi>
               </note>Such ſecrets as <hi>Eye hath not ſeene, neither eare heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can it enter into the heart of man to conceive.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.10. to inſtance in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars. The firſt ſecret is the pardon of ſinne, the moſt bleſſed newes and moſt joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3510:31"/>
tidings that can come to the ſoule of a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when the ſoule with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Pſal.</hi> 88.7. lyeth crying day and night under the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of the Lord, with <hi>David</hi> roaring for very diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe of Spirit, with <hi>Iob</hi> the arrowes of the Lord drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us its ſpirit, then for Chriſt to whiſper unto the ſoule in ſecret by his Spirit, and to ſay unto it, Spouſe be of good comfort, <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgiven thee,</hi> this is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Chriſt will communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to none, but unto his ſpouſe.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, how may a poore ſoule know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this voyce of Chriſt by his ſpirit be not a deluſion of Satan?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3510:32"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill can ſuggeſt falſely into his owne children, what Chriſt in truth ſuggeſts into the hearts of his owne people, and that often he can counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferfeite this teſtimony of the Spirit concerning the pardon of ſinne, putting in thoughts of comfort, mercy and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinne, and of peace to the ſoule, when God makes himſelfe ready for Warre. But by this may Chriſts voyce comforting the ſoule be knowne from Sathans flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries and falſe perſwaſions,<note place="margin">How Chriſts voyce is known from Sathans illuſion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the pardon of ſin.</note> from the time and condition the ſoule is in, when theſe thoughts of Mercy and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of pardon of ſinne come unto the ſoule, if the ſoule (as before) be in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſolate
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3510:32"/>
condition by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſenſe of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſinne, and deepe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Gods wrath, then for the ſoule to receive comfort, and to entertaine thoughts of mercy, lifting up the ſoule as it were from the gates of hell, to the ſuburbs of heaven; this is a good ſigne it is the work of Chriſt and his voyce by his Spirit communicating this ſecret of mercy and pardon of ſinne, becauſe this is againſt the policy of Sathan to comfort the ſoule, and to lift it up when it is in ſinking through the ſenſe of Gods wrath, but on the contrary, his ordinary courſe is when the ſoule is in heavineſſe, dejection and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and inclining to deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3510:33"/>
to follow the ſoule cloſe, to drive it into the further degree of deſpaire, till it be ſwallowed up of it. But if the ſoule ſhal have thoughts of mercy, and aſſurance of ſalvation ſuggeſted into it, when it hath never felt the burden of ſinne, the ſpirit of bondage, never beene truely humbled for ſinne, this is a ſigne of an illuſion of Sathan to drive the ſoule to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh by preſumption, which is a more frequent Rocke, againſt which the ſoule ſplits it ſelfe, than deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond ſecret is the experimentall knowledge of the worke of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a ſecret and myſterie that few are privie unto.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3510:33"/>
               <hi>Nicodemus</hi> though a teacher in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet ignorant in this point till Chriſt inſtructed him in it, and at Chriſts firſt relating of it unto him it ſeemed a<note n="(s)" place="margin">What a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable is regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to many even old men, Maſters, and teachers, and rulers in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who knew no other nativity but one of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> no progenie of God and his Church, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parents but ſuch as beger earthly chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall life, &amp;c. D. <hi>Taylor</hi> on <hi>Tit. p.</hi> 65.</note> riddle unto him, till Chriſt ſhewed him how, and in what manner it was wrought, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.4.5. Many can talke of the dangers of Warre, of the wonders of the Sea, of the Indies and remote places, who yet never were in warre, upon the ſea, or in any fore-mentioned Countries, but they that have beene in hot skirmiſhes of warre, that have gone down into the deepe, and occupied ſhips in the great waters, they that have ſeene the Indies and remote places; have bought their knowledge at a deare
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3510:34"/>
rate of hard labour, great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and long travaile, the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of theſe is this, the one know by heare-ſay, by reading, and the like, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by experience: it is ſo in preſent caſe, we may heare one ſpeaking of regeneration, another diſputing of it, and both ignorant of it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of any experimentall knowledge, but the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians knowledge of the work of grace is experimentall, he can tell the method that God uſed in the new framing and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> regenerating of his heart. Firſt that God humbled him by the terrour of the Law, and ſo unbottomed his heart, and tooke him off on himſelfe, by a thorough conviction of his loſt condition out of Chriſt,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3510:34"/>
that God broke his heart in pieces by the hammer of his Word, and threatning of the Law, that then he thawed and diſſolved his frozen heart, by the ſweete Evangelicall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and thoſe comfortable Revelations of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the Lord of life, unto his ſoule, that hee then formed Chriſt day by day, mortifying his ſinne by degrees, and every day giving the ſoule a greater meaſure of inward quickning and vivification to the life of holineſſe and righteouſneſſe; this ſecret worke of regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Chriſt communicates onely to his Spouſe.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall I know may ſome ſay,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> whether Chriſt hath commonicated this ſecret worke of regeneration to me or not?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3510:35"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> There are many things that go for regeneration in the world that are no more true regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration than the picture that <hi>Michal</hi> layd in the bed for <hi>David</hi> was like unto <hi>David,</hi> whereby ſhe would have delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the meſſengers of <hi>Saul,</hi> as morality, ceſſation from groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſinnes, partiall obedience and the like; all which and many are but faire colours to paint over an unregenerate <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> heart. For firſt, regeneration is a renewing of the inward man, theſe the ſlicking over of the outward man, rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is a mortifying of the inward Principles of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and a killing of ſinne at the roote, theſe but like ſo many loppings and plaſhings of ſinne in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3510:35"/>
branches, regeneration is a metamorphoſing of the heart, theſe but changes of the outward converſation in ſome meaſure, againe theſe differ from regeneration in the cauſe. Civill honeſty,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ceſſation of groſſe ſinnes, partiall obedience and the like, may proceede firſt from education, as they did who lived in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Lutherans:</hi> ſo many being ſtems growing of a religious ſtocke, brought up under carefull and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Maſters, tutors, and guardians, are many times civiliſed, and yet made not at all acquainted with the ſecret worke of mans regeneration, than that which goes any further than the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3510:36"/>
outward carriage and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ceſſation from groſſe ſinnes may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from a naturall kinde of conſcience that may bee even in men that are but in the ſtate of nature,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.1.</note> ſo <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of ſuch a fornication as was not named amongſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, that is, the Heathens made conſcience of ſuch a kinde of fornication. <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi> an Heathen abſtained from <hi>Sarah, Abrahams</hi> wife, and God aſcribes it to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of his heart. <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.6.<note place="margin">Num. 22.18.</note> 
               <hi>Balaam</hi> that wicked ſorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer would not at the firſt goe againſt the Commandement of the Lord for an houſe full of gold and ſilver; ſo <hi>Hazael</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Is thy ſervant a dogge that I ſhould doe this
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3510:36"/>
thing;</hi> he abhorres it at the firſt hearing as an horrid wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, becomming a dog better than a man: by all which inſtances it appeares that a man may abſtaine from many groſſe ſinnes, out of a naturall and carnall conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereas regeneration brings reformation from a conſcience purified and ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled with the blood of Chriſt. Theſe things to wit morality, &amp;c. may proceed from ingenuity of nature, and from a reſtraining grace that God puts into the hearts of many unregenerate men, which grace if God ſhould not give it to ſome men, man by nature would be more<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. 1. Pol. c. 2.</note> ſavage than the Beare, more truculent than the Tyger,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3510:37"/>
more cruell than the Wolfe of the morning, more brutiſh than the beaſts of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. Theſe may proceede in the fourth place from feare of the loſſe of reputation, men are loath to bee counted the ſcumme of the world, the raffle of the people, the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of their generation, hence the feare of diſgrace ſwayes their hearts to a more reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned life, from the groſſer pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the world, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation proceedes from other principles, not meerely from education (though that is a meanes many times ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God to further it) not from ingenuity of nature, feare of ignominy, but from the worke of Gods Spirit, opening the eyes of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3510:37"/>
ranſaking the conſcience, and laying it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, ſubjugating the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous will, turning the ſtreames of the affections into the right channels, and upon the right objects, purifying and cleanſing the whole man in all the powers of the ſoule and members of the body, this ſecret worke that is knowne to few doth Chriſt acquaint his Spouſe with all, that the Spouſe is able to ſay concerning the recovery of Spirituall ſight, and other parts of regeneration, as the blind man of his corporall fight.<note place="margin">Iohn 9.25.</note> One thing I know and that by experience, that I was blind in my ſoule and now I ſee, that I was dead in ſinne, but now I am alive and borne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3510:38"/>
againe unto God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third ſecret that Chriſt reveales unto his ſpouſe is the deformity of ſinne; man in ſtate of nature lookes upon ſinne not as it is in it ſelfe, the greateſt evill, but as it hath the forme of ſome counterfeit good; for as the Devill can transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light, ſo can he transforme his workes, and put on them a faire gloſſe, to make them more vendible commodities to vent to the men of this world in exchange for their precious ſoules: neither is the Devill more readie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, than man ſubject to be deceived in his view and judging of ſinne, as the<note n="(o)" place="margin">Voluntatis propenſi auto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem vitiis quaerit, &amp; quod malum eſt bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num aut bono proximum eſſe fuadet. <hi>Aug. Serm.</hi> 12. <hi>de Tempore.</hi>
               </note> Father obſerves, perſwading
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3510:38"/>
himſelfe that the ſinne hee is tempted unto is either no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, or not ſo great an evill as really it is.<note n="(w)" place="margin">Hypocrit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vitrum ponit loco veri mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariti. <hi>Ifidorus Pelien ſiot. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 24.</note> An hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite (as one well obſerveth) puts a glaſſe in place of a pearle, that is, ſheweth forth his counterfeit and worthleſſe performances as if they were precious things, and if hee hath committed ſinne, with the harlot hee wipeth his mouth, ſaying what evill have I done? but when Chriſt once eſpouſeth himſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſoule, hee takes off the faire colours wherewith ſinne hath ſhadowed it ſelf withall, and preſents him to the ſoule in its owne proper ſhape and ugly hue: ſo as the Prophet <hi>Ahijah,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 14.6. diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the wife of <hi>Ieroboam</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:3510:39"/>
diſguiſed, ſo the ſoule endued with the Spirit of Chriſt can diſcerne the deformity of ſinne though never ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly and curiouſly diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Art of Sathan: from this true ſight of ſinne, ariſeth that deteſtation of ſinne in the heart of a Chriſtian, that he thinkes it a more fearefull ſight to behold the horrid face of ſinne committed in his ſoule, than to behold the Lake of Brimſtone in the loweſt hell: hence was it that holy<note n="(x)" place="margin">Et ſi multi gehennam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium malorum ſupremum atque ultimum putant. Ego tamen ſic cenſeo, ſic affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duò predicabo, multo acerbius eſſe Chriſtum offendere, quam gehennae malis vexari <hi>Chryſoſt. in Mat. Hom.</hi> 37.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> affirmed this to bee a truth that hee would dayly Preach. That it was a more bitter and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing to offend Chriſt than to be tormented with the flames of hell it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth ſecret that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3510:39"/>
Chriſt communicates to his Spouſe is the vanity and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of the Creatures. Man lookes upon the world, and the vanity thereof as a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and amiable object, hee lookes upon worldly things as his ſubſtance, his profit, his glory, but Chriſt ſhewes unto his Spouſe that riches in ſteade of being glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, are but as thicke clay.<note place="margin">Hab. 2.6. ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard riches compared to clay.</note> 
               <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.6. which is, firſt a common thing at every mans doore: ſecondly, a ſoyling thing: thirdly, a ſlippery thing. So riches but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bleſſings, polluting the poſſeſſors of them, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their Conſciences, ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery they are alſo and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, taking wings they flye away. Againe Chriſt ſheweth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3510:40"/>
his ſpouſe that wordly things are not ſubſtance but ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.6. not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits but loſſes being compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the true gaine, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.11.12. A naturall man priſeth pleaſure as his great <hi>Diana,</hi> preferment as the top of happineſſe, but Chriſts Spouſe is acquainted with this ſecret by her husband, that the one is vanity, and the other but a ſpiders web. He that is unskilfull in the Arts and Sciences and lookes upon the earth, thinkes it to be ſome ſpacious and great body, and admires it for its immenſity: but let the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematitian come and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the earth and the heavens together, he knowes upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible demonſtrations, that
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3510:40"/>
the body of the earth is but like a<note n="(y)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ariſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> Meteorolog. c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> point or nothing being compared with the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference of the heavens: So let a man never inſtructed by Chriſt; looke upon earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, hee admires them for their excellencie; but let a Chriſtian (whom Chriſt hath taught this leſſon of the vanity of the creature) come to judge of theſe outward and ſublunary things and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with heavenly things, with grace, with Chriſt, with glory, with hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, hee findes them being weighed with theſe to bee lighter than vanity it ſelfe. Let <hi>Paul</hi> be judge, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted all things but dung in regard of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The fifth ſecret is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3510:41"/>
of Chriſt. <hi>Mark.</hi> 4.11. Chriſt tells his Diſciples that <hi>to them it was given to know the myſteries of the Kingdome of God; but to them that were without all things were done in Parables, that ſeeing they might not ſee, &amp;c.</hi> a naturall man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives not the things of God and thoſe glorious excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that are in Chriſt: though there be abundance of light, beauty, and glory in the Sun, yet a man that is borne blinde cannot ſee any of them: it is ſo with the natural man in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Sonne of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, there is abundance of light, beauty, glory, heate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing, and reviving vertue in Chriſt, yet none of theſe can the naturall man ſee. <hi>Cant.</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:3510:41"/>
5.9. There are ſome that askes Chriſts Spouſe what ſhe ſaw in her beloved, that made her ſicke of love, thereby intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that they for their parts ſaw no ſuch amiableneſſe in him, but the ſpouſe anſweres that ſhe ſaw ſomething in him that did attract her heart to him, <hi>My beloved</hi> ſaith ſhe, <hi>is white and ruddie, the chiefeſt of ten thouſand:</hi> though the men of the world ſee nothing in Chriſt deſireable and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet his ſpouſe ſees his eminent excellencies which Chriſt revealeth to her by his Spirit, and therefore <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.17. <hi>Peter</hi> confeſſeth Chriſt to be the Sonne of God, and ſo perceiving ſalvation by him alone. Chriſt tells him that fleſh and blood had not
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3510:42"/>
revealed that unto him, but his Father which is in heaven, the excellencies in Chriſt diſcerned onely of the Saints, are priſed and deſired onely of them, hence was it that <hi>Peter</hi> deſired to abide in Chriſts preſence; <hi>Lord whether ſhall we goe? thou haſt the Words of eternall life:</hi> and having but a taſte of Chriſts excellencie and glory in the transfigura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he cryed, <hi>It is good to be here. Peter</hi> had beene in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent places for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight, but never ſaid before, <hi>It is good to be here:</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting wife, lands, and living he cryes. <hi>It is good to be here,</hi> ſo ſweete is the preſence of the Lord Jeſus, eſpecially when the ſoule obtaines a ſight of his excellencies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:3510:42"/>A ſixth ſecret is the gaine <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> of godlineſſe, a ſecret that the worldling is ignorant of, that counts gaine to be God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, as the Apoſtle ſpeakes 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. A man of this world thinkes there is no profit but in purchaſing of Lands and revenewes, no honour but in the favour of earthly Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates, no beauty but that of the body, no pleaſure but in Epicuriſme, ſurfetting, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, chambering, and wantonneſſe; but Chriſt ſhews his ſpouſe againe in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Secondly, honour in being in favour at the Court of heaven. Thirdly, beauty in grace: and laſtly pleaſure in walking in the wayes of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> God. Firſt, Chriſt ſhewes his Spouſe a gaine in godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3510:43"/>
this Chriſt had taught bleſſed <hi>Paul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.7.</note> thoſe things that were gaine to him he counted loſſe for Chriſt, Chriſt being ſufficient gaine to him as he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voucheth,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>For me to live is Chriſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and to dye is gaine.</hi> Secondly, honour in the favour of God, this the Pſalmiſt was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted withall. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.9. concluding the Pſalme with this Epiphonema: <hi>Such honour have all his Saints.</hi> This Saint <hi>Luke</hi> knew well, who ſtiles <hi>Theophilus</hi> a lover of God, moſt Noble <hi>Theophilus, Luke</hi> 1.3. and the <hi>Bereans</hi> more honourable than them of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> for their piety and devotion, this <hi>David</hi> knew well when hee deſired rather to be a doore keeper in the houſe of God, than to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3510:43"/>
dwell in the tents of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. Thirdly, Beauty in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> grace,<note n="(q)" place="margin">Non defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate corporis animius faeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſed pulchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine animi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corpus ornatur. <hi>Senica.</hi>
               </note> this ſecret <hi>Salomon</hi> knew when he affirmes <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Wiſedome maketh the face to ſhine.</hi> Laſtly, pleaſure in the wayes of God, and the pathes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> of righteouſneſſe: this <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> avoucheth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17. <hi>The wayes of Wiſedome are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſſe, and all her pathes peace,</hi> this <hi>David</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>Thy teſtimonies are my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, ſweeter unto me than the honey and honey combe:</hi> to this purpoſe cryed holy <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">O luxurioſe ubi major delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio quam in Gemmè dulciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimo deo, <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> O thou luxurious fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, where is there greater pleaſure to bee found than in the ſweeteſt God, and in his ſervice; this myſtery cannot enter into the heart of a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall-man, that there ſhould be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3510:44"/>
ſuch pleaſure in the wayes of God,<note place="margin">Tam amant le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem quam ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micida carce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> who ordinarily loves the houſe of God, and the Lawes of God as a Murtherer doth the priſon: as <hi>Luther</hi> was wont to ſay: a naturall man findes no more ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Chriſt and his wayes, than there is taſte in the white of an egge. <hi>Iob</hi> 6.6. or than <hi>Barzillai</hi> found in the meate that King <hi>David</hi> would have given him to eate, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.35. but the Spouſe of Chriſt having had a taſte of Gods goodneſſe, and an experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall relliſh of the wayes of God, and the pleaſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, affirmes of Gods ſervice in generall, as <hi>David</hi> did of his ſervice in Gods houſe; <hi>One day in Gods Courts are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a thouſand.</hi> So that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3510:44"/>
as Chriſt ſayd to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: he had bread they knew not of, which was to doe the will of his Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the like may a beleever ſay to a worldly and ſinnefull man, hee hath meate and drinke, pleaſure and recreation that they know not of, neither did ever taſte, which is to doe the will, and walke in the pathes of Chriſt his Lord and husband.</p>
            <p>A ſeventh ſecret is a taſte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> of the joy of heaven, as the wicked taſte of hell before they come into the locall place thereof, by moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full horrors of Conſcience which are as flaſhes of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiveably tormenting fire of the Tophet, that is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the devill and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3510:45"/>
ſo the godly many times have a taſte of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utterable and infinitly delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full joy in heaven, before they take ful poſſeſſion thereof: the ſpies that went into <hi>Canaan</hi> brought backe with them ſome cluſters of Grapes, to ſhew the fruitfulneſſe of the land. Chriſt in like manner gives the ſoule ſome cluſters of Grapes, ſome taſte of that goodneſſe of <hi>Canaan</hi> above, that his Spouſe feeling the delight of that Country, may not deſire any continuing City here, but looke for one that is above: this taſte of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſometimes God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his Saints in an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary manner, as he did to <hi>Paul</hi> in his rapture into the third heaven, unto <hi>Steven</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:3510:45"/>
when the heavens were ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and he ſaw the Sonne of God ſtanding on the right hand of his Father, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary revelations with all other <hi>Euthuſiaſmes,</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſticall dreames and fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, God communicates not to his Saints in this latter age of the world: therefore a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and ordinary way wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God ſhewes the ſoule a ſight of heaven, and a taſte of the pleaſure thereof is by the eye of faith, by the aſſurance of Salvation, by the witneſſe of the Spirit with our owne Spirit, by giving the ſoule ſuch an inward ſenſe and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his favour, and ſuch a ſtedfaſt hope upon ſolide grounds of heaven, by begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heavenly Muſique by
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3510:46"/>
of a good conſcience, and by raiſing up the ſoule by the unſpeakable peace of God, and joy of the Holy-ghoſt: by theſe and the like meanes doth God give the ſoule a taſte of heaven, and as <hi>Moſes</hi> upon <hi>Piſgah</hi> ſaw <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo in theſe as upon <hi>Piſgah</hi> doth Chriſt carry his Spouſe to ſee <hi>Canaan</hi> that is above, the joynture that he will inſtall his ſpouſe into.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond conſequent on Chriſts part.</note>The ſecond conſequent on Chriſts part is a communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of goods, as a man by his marriage endues his wife with all his worldly goods, ſo Chriſt endues his ſpouſe with his goods. All things are common, ſaith the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Anima quae diligit Deum ſponſa vocatur haec enim duo nomina, ſponſa &amp; ſponſus, maximè in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant internos affectus, hic e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim omnia communia ſunt, una haereditas, una domus, una menſa, unus le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, una caro. <hi>Bern ſerm.</hi> 7. <hi>in Cantio.</hi>
               </note> Father, betwixt man and wife, one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, one houſe, one
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3510:46"/>
Table, one bed, one fleſh: the goods that Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates to his Spouſe are of three ſorts. Firſt externall, there is communication of outward comforts ſo farre forth as ſhall conduce to his owne glory and the good of his ſpouſe. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.21. <hi>In that day,</hi> to wit of his marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with his people, <hi>I will heare the heavens, the heavens ſhall heare the earth, the earth ſhall heare the corne, wine, and oyle, and they ſhall heare Iſrael:</hi> and the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the beleeving <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to whom Chriſt was eſpouſed, tells them 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.21. All things were theirs, <hi>Paul, Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> things preſent and to come: the ground of this was becauſe <hi>they were Chriſts and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3510:47"/>
Chriſt Gods.</hi> Secondly, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. In Chriſt to his Spouſe there is a communication of grace. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.16. <hi>Of his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we receive grace for grace:</hi> in Chriſt there is a fulneſſe of grace, there is not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a ſufficiencie, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a redundancie of grace, as <hi>Plato</hi> diſtinguiſheth. In Chriſt, there is not onely the fulneſſe of a veſſell that may be full in it ſelfe, but if it part with any liquor to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther veſſels, its owne proper fulneſſe is diminiſhed, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there is a fulneſſe of a fountaine that is not onely full in it ſelfe and for it ſelfe, but it can communicate to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in its fulneſſe without diminution of its owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per fulneſſe, this kind of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3510:47"/>
is in Chriſt the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of grace and inexha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible wel-ſpring of Life, this fulneſſe of grace in Chriſt was that oyle wherewith hee is ſaid to be annointed above his fellowes, and not by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for that oyle was not any typicall and Sacramentall oyle, wherewith the Prieſts, Prophets, and Kings were annointed in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but the Spirituall oyle of Gods grace, called the oyle of gladneſſe, which oyle was powred on Chriſts head in ſo plentifull a manner that like the oyntment powred on <hi>Aarons</hi> head, it went downe to the skirts of his garment. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.2. ſo this oyle of Gods grace powred on Chriſt the head of his ſpouſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3510:48"/>
diſtils into the skirts of his garment, into his meaneſt member, ſo that there is no humility, meekeneſſe, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, love, heavenly minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe nor any other grace in Chriſt, but ſome influence of that grace diſtils into the heart of every one eſpouſed unto him, hence the Apoſtle affirmes 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.8. that God is ſo full of grace, and hath ſuch a ſufficiencie, that is, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to others: in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall the Apoſtle emphatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſeth this by triplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.8. opened.</note> Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not in one, but in every neceſſitie. Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times but at every time. Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not ſome ſufficiencie, but a ſufficiencie
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3510:48"/>
of every grace. Eternall. In Chriſt there is a communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of glory to his ſpouſe. Chriſt will have no glory in heaven but in part, and ſo far forth, as his ſpouſe is capable of, he will<note n="(b)" place="margin">Anina quae nunc pannoſo veſtitu, ac ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili habitu regi putatur, in reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no caelorum regina &amp; nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis Regi aſtans reperitur <hi>Baſil. l. de vera. virg.</hi>
               </note> communicate that glory unto his ſpouſe. So <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.22.24. Chriſt ſaith to his Father, <hi>The glory which thou gaveſt me I have given them, that they may be one as wee are one;</hi> and againe, <hi>Father I will that they alſo whom thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me, be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory which thou haſt given mee, for thou lovedſt me before the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſequents <hi>ex parte ſponſae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents</hi> ex parte ſponſae.</note> or on the beleevers part, follow which are two</p>
            <p>Firſt a whole change.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:3510:49"/>Secondly, a familiar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> A whole change anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the change in a woman after ſhee is eſpouſed to her husband, which is of three things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Of Name.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Of Quality and Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Of Barrenneſſe into Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>There is a change of name in a woman newly eſpouſed,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Martia redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re voleus ad Catonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ait, da tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum nomen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ane Connubii, liceat tumulo ſcripſiſſe, Cato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis <hi>Martia. Luc. l.</hi> 2.</note> women change their owne name into the name of their husbands, ſo the <hi>Roman</hi> wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tooke the name of their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, ſo<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>valer. l.</hi> 10 Iſaiah. 4.1. Iohn. 19.25.</note> 
               <hi>Caja</hi> from her husband <hi>Cajus, Tullia</hi> from her husband <hi>Tullius,</hi> and the like. So amongſt the <hi>Iewes Mary</hi> of <hi>Cleophas,</hi> to wit the wife of <hi>Cleophas:</hi> hence ſome
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3510:49"/>
thinke the Spouſe in the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> is called <hi>Sulamitis</hi> or <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamite.</hi> q. d. <hi>Solomonia</hi> from <hi>Solomon</hi> her husband. In like manner doth Chriſts Spouſe change her name being once married to him. <hi>Abram</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring into covenant with God changed his name into <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Sarai</hi> into <hi>Sarah. Iacob</hi> prevailing with Chriſt chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his name into <hi>Iſrael; Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> muſt be called <hi>Peter, Saul</hi> converted was called <hi>Paul:</hi> ſo every ſoule eſpouſed to Chriſt hath a new name; of a childe of perdition called a ſonne or daughter of God by adoption; of a limbe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than a member of Chriſt, of a veſſell of wrath, a veſſell of honour, of an aliant and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from Chriſt becomes a
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3510:50"/>
Chriſtian, ſo that as <hi>Naomi</hi> ſayd in another caſe:<note place="margin">Iohn 15.15.</note> 
               <hi>Call me no more Naomi, but call me Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, for the Lord hath afflicted me:</hi> ſo may the Spouſe of Chriſt ſay on the contrary, call me no more <hi>Marah</hi> but <hi>Nao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi</hi> for the Lord hath viſited me, no more deſolate and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken but <hi>Hephziba,</hi> but <hi>Beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah,</hi> the delight of the Lord, the Spouſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">May 62.4.5.</note> as the Prophet ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond change is of Nature and quality. A wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the time of her virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity may be addicted to vaine ſports, and paſtimes, which after her eſpouſing to an hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſhee abhorres; ſo a Chriſtian before hee come to be betrothed to Chriſt may be given to many vaine
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3510:50"/>
delights of fleſh and blood, which after his betrothing to Chriſt he abandons and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres. The Apoſtle ſpeaking to the beleeving Romans eſpouſed to Chriſt. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. affirmes that they deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in thoſe things in their naturall eſtate, whereof being in Chriſt they were aſhamed. <hi>What fruite had you in thoſe things whereof ye are now aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med:</hi> the like change in that young convert of whom S.<note n="(e)" place="margin">Ambroſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> de praviten. c. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> maketh mention wch anſwered his <hi>quondam</hi> Curti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan that came to him with this ſalutation, <hi>Ego ſum:</hi> It is I: the bleſſed young con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert newly eſpouſed to Chriſt anſwered, <hi>At Ego non ſum Ego,</hi> I am not I. I am wholly changed into another Man, of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3510:51"/>
a ſinner made a Saint, of a vaſſall of my baſe luſts made a veſſell of honour, and the very Spouſe of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: ſuch a change was in <hi>Paul</hi> that <hi>Ananias</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred he ſhould be ſent to <hi>Saul</hi> when he heard what evill he had done to the Saints,<note place="margin">Acts 9.13.</note> and <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.13. that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> even above meaſure hee had made havocke of the Saints, yet the ſame <hi>Saul</hi> of a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor becomes a Preacher, of an enemie he became a friend to Chriſt, the like change in <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> whoſe ſoule was as a burrough to harbour uncleane ſpirits, as a cage of uncleane birds, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was made a Temple of the holy Spirit, and her heart
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3510:51"/>
a pallace to entertaine the Lord Jeſus with the deareſt affection: ſo powerfull is the Lord Jeſus to make his Spouſe like unto himſelfe. <hi>Moſes</hi> his face may ſhine, but the glory of his face could not make his garments glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious that were about him. Chriſt his body upon Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> was transfigured and the glory thereof diſplayed it ſelfe through his very gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the ſame Jeſus Chriſt being now transfigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in full glory in heaven, is ſo full of grace, that hee can communicate grace to his meaneſt member. <hi>Moſes</hi> may marry an <hi>Aethiopian,</hi> but hee cannot change her blacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Chriſt making love to a poore ſoule of an <hi>Aethiopian</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:3510:52"/>
dye, full of Leopards ſpots, can ſo change this ſoule and renew it day by day till hee make it a pure virgin, and preſent it unto himſelfe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot and wrinckle. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. ſo the Lord affirmes, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.7.8. that when he paſſed by his people, he ſaw them wallowing in their blood, but hee ſoone waſhed them and made them beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third change is of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe into fruitfulneſſe. A woman, though barren in the time of her virginity, growes after marriage for the moſt part fruitefull, that her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren like Olive branches ſit round about her Table, ſo a Chriſtian, though before his marriage with Chriſt he bee
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3510:52"/>
fruitleſſe and barren in good workes, yet after this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all betrothing growes fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and abundant in the work of the Lord. This the Apoſtle makes the end of beleevers marriage with Chriſt, that they may bring forth<note n="(f)" place="margin">Dum anima adhaeret ſponſo ſuo, &amp; audit verbum ejus, &amp; ipſum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectitur, ſine dubio ab ipſo ſemen ſuſcipit, inde naſcetur generoſa pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genies, inde pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicitia orietur, inde juſtitia, inde patientia, inde manſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, &amp; charitas atque omnium virtutum proles veneranda ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedet. <hi>Origen. Hom.</hi> 20. <hi>in</hi> 25. <hi>Numb.</hi>
               </note> fruits unto God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.4. and our Saviour makes fruitfulneſſe in good workes one fruite of a beleevers union with Chriſt. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.5. It cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed but that an unregenerate perſon not betrothed to Chriſt may doe ſome workes, and bring forth ſome fruites good for the matter, but theſe workes and fruites brought forth before his ſpirituall Marriage, are but like the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren a woman beares before her marriage, which are ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3510:53"/>
and illegitimate brats that cannot inherite, ſo the good workes of unregenerate men are illegitimate and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<note n="(g)" place="margin">Articles of Religion. <hi>Article. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</hi>
               </note> inherite being brought forth out of Spirituall wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, and not flowing from the right roote, which is faith in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers part.</note>The ſecond conſequent on the beleevers part is a familiar acquaintance with Chriſt, that a beleever can upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the greateſt ſtraights goe unto Chriſt, and make his wants knowne unto him. Such an acquaintance had <hi>Moſes</hi> with God.<note place="margin">Ioſhua. 20.12.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.11. by the holding up of whoſe hand <hi>Iſrael</hi> prevailed: ſuch an acquaintance had <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah,</hi> who by his prayer cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Sunne to ſtand ſtill
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3510:53"/>
upon <hi>Gibeon</hi> and the Moone in the valley of <hi>Ajelon,</hi> and ſuch an acquaintance and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timateneſſe hath the Spouſe of Chriſt with Chriſt, that upon all occaſions, if any thing perplexe and moleſt the ſoule, it can goe unto Chriſt and make its caſe knowne unto him, with a full perſwaſion that he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and comfort it, neither hath the ſoule acquaintance onely with Chriſt, but by Chriſt with the Father and the bleſſed Spirit: as <hi>Iſaac</hi> taking <hi>Rebecca</hi> to be his wiſe brought her into his mothers tent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.67: So Chriſt marrying a beleeving ſoule, brings that ſoule into his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers preſence to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him; this the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3510:54"/>
Apoſtle ſweetely expreſſeth. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.12.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12. opened.</note> 
               <hi>In whom we have boldneſſe and acceſſe;</hi> the word boldneſſe in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and it ſignifieth bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of face in ſpeaking, ſhewing that a beleever by Chriſt hath boldneſſe to goe to God by prayer, againe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>in him,</hi> that is Chriſt, <hi>we have not onely bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse but acceſſe:</hi> in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ſuch an acceſſe which is by manuduction as <hi>Iſaac</hi> took <hi>Rebecca;</hi> ſo Chriſt takes the ſoule eſpouſed to him by the hand, and leads it into his Fathers preſence, and into ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, ſo that the ſoule which before this ſpirituall marriage was a ſtranger to God, and God an
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3510:54"/>
angry God with the ſoule through ſinne, now appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends God in Chriſt reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and an indulgent Father: and laſt of all the Apoſtle ſheweth how the beleever hath this boldneſſe of ſpeech, this acceſſe, and this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, it is by faith of him, faith is the eye of the ſoule by which the ſoule lookes upon God reconciled. Now as to the bodily ſight there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not onely a well diſpoſed Organ, but a<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ariſt. l. 2. de Anima. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>perſpicuous medium,</hi> a lightſome ayre or the like, through which the ſpecies of the viſible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, muſt be received into the Organ of the eye: ſo in the ſpirituall ſight of the ſoule which it hath of God, there is required a diaphanous and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3510:55"/>
perſpicuous <hi>medium,</hi> which is Chriſt the mediator, through whom the ſoule by faith ſees him that is inviſible, it is Chriſt that drawes neere unto God for his friends. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.17. and they draw neere to God by Chriſt. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19.22.<note place="margin">The application of this ſubject.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The application of this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> point is fourefold, the firſt is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for inſtruction in two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. Firſt, it teacheth the dignity of the Saints. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the duty of the Saints. Firſt their<note n="(i)" place="margin">Vnde tibi ô humana anima unde tibi hoc, unde tam in aeſtimabilis glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, ut ejus ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa merearis eſſe in quem deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ant Angeli proſpicere? unde tibi hoc, ut ipſe fit ſponſus tuus cujus pulcritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Sol &amp; Luna mirantur, ad cujus nutum univerſa mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur. <hi>Bern. Ser.</hi> 2. <hi>Dom,</hi> 1. <hi>poſt. Epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>David</hi> thought it a great dignity to match into the ſtocke of <hi>Saul</hi> that was King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Who am I, &amp;c.</hi> greater honour and dignity it is to match into the ſtocke of God even unto
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3510:55"/>
his onely begotten ſonne, and ſo to be called the Kings daughter, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. The Kings Spouſe and beloved; well may the ſoule enter into an holy admiration of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; and cry out with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Lord what is man? or the Sonne of man that thou ſo regardeſt him,</hi> and haſt crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with ſo great a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as to bee called the Spouſe of Chriſt; who (as <hi>Abigail</hi> ſayd to <hi>David</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring marriage) I am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to waſh the feete of the Lords Servants. It was a great dignity for <hi>Ruth</hi> to bee eſpouſed to <hi>Boaz;</hi> but a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honour and favour for a poore ſoule to be married to Chriſt, whoſe nature is good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whoſe greatneſſe is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſſe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3510:56"/>
whoſe power is omnipotencie, whoſe worke is mercy, whoſe anger is ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, whoſe throne is ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, whoſe will is equity, whoſe life is felicity, and whoſe age is eternity. Let the heavens ſtand amazed at this honour and favour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> compariſon. Secondly, this point teacheth the duty of the Saints, that ſeeing they are the Spouſe of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Chriſt. Firſt then they muſt adorne themſelves that Chriſt may take delight in them; all delight proceedes from ſome correſpondencie in comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, affection, and action. The Heathen<note n="(k)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. 1. Oec. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher could ſay that diſſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of manners, and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of carriage is not apt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3510:56"/>
to beget or preſerve love and delight: ſo that Chriſt may take content and delight in his Saints eſpouſed unto himſelfe, they muſt adorne themſelves whereby they may become like unto him, hee is cloathed with holineſſe and righteouſneſſe as with a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he is full of beauty and enamouring comelineſſe, that like then may rejoyce in like, the ſoule muſt bee adorned that Chriſt may ſay of the ſoule as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did of <hi>Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah. Iudg.</hi> 14.3. <hi>She pleaſeth me well;</hi> this the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.14. <hi>The Kings daughter ſhall bee brought unto the King in a ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of needle worke, ſo ſhall the King,</hi> that is Chriſt, <hi>take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in her beauty:</hi> if it be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3510:57"/>
what this needleworke of divers colours is. I anſwere not any outward ornament mentioned <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.18.19.20. not that ſtrange apparell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Prophet, <hi>Zephan.</hi> 1.8.<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Oeconom. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Theſe outward ornaments are not the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherewith Chriſts Spouſe muſt be cloathed, that Chriſt may take delight in her, theſe make the ſoule many times more deformed in the ſight of Chriſt, theſe are the worlds Livery, which the ſervants of the world for the moſt part are cloathed withall; therefore the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 45.13. expreſſeth what the ornaments of Chriſts Spouſe are. <hi>The Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is all glorious within,</hi> the<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Septuagints</hi> read the words
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3510:57"/>
thus; <hi>All the glory of the Kings daughter is within.</hi> A beleever in outward appearance hath little glory, therefore the Church complaines. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.5. <hi>I am blacke but comely,</hi> blacke in the opinion of the world not ſeeing my beauty which is inward; blacke through perſecution and the ſcorching flames thereof, but comely in the eyes of Chriſt, who lookes on my inward beauty that cannot be ſeene by the world: ſo then the inward<note n="(n)" place="margin">In ſola ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pulchritudo, &amp; turpitudo apparent, &amp; ideo is ſolus verè puicher eſt, qui eſt vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute praeditus <hi>Clem. Ale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an. Padog. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. Illis ampla ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis forma pudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citia. <hi>Tibullus. Elig. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Eleg.</hi> 2. Palchritudo tua fit bona vita, ſtude itaque placere Chriſto, non pretioſis veſtibus, ſed bonis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oribus non pulchritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine carmò, ſed pulchritudine mentis. <hi>Beru. de modo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vivend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Sor.</hi> 9. Ezek. 16.8.9.10.</note> ornaments wherewith Chriſts Spouſe muſt adorne her ſelfe are the heavenly diſpoſitions, vertues, qualities, and graces of the ſoule; as humility, meekeneſſe, temperance, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, brotherly kindneſſe, heavenly mindedneſſe, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3510:58"/>
the like. This the Apoſtle inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.13. <hi>Put on therefore as the elect of God, holy and beloved, bowels of mercies, kindneſſe, humbleneſſe of minde, meekeneſse, long ſuffering, &amp;c. put on,</hi> the word in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>put on</hi> as a garment or ornament, and the garment it ſelfe is a concati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of graces, a troope of heavenly vertues; as mercy, kindneſſe, humility, &amp;c. this is the needle worke of divers colours wherewith the Kings daughter muſt bee adorned when ſhe is preſented to the King, called a needle worke of divers colours, in regard of the variety of graces that this needle-worke conſiſts of, as alſo noteing the glory of this ornament of grace and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3510:58"/>
holineſſe, for as diverſity of colours in needleworke, ſo variety of graces make a ſoule more beautifull and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, every grace having its diſtinct beauty and luſter, and all of them being joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one ſoule, one grace gives a glory unto another, all of them together ſhining in the ſoule, like ſo many dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds in a Ring. Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this teacheth the Saints, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond duety to preſerve their ſpirituall chaſtitie, and to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves as pure virgines towards their husband Chriſt: the Apoſtle tels the beleeving <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that he was jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous over them with godly jealouſie; for he had eſpouſed them to one husband,<note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.2.</note> that he might preſent them as a
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3510:59"/>
chaſte virgin to Chriſt, and this jealouſie that <hi>Paul</hi> had over the beleeving <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſhould every beleeving ſoule have over it ſelfe, that Chriſt may have no occaſion to bee jealous of the ſoules entire affection to himſelfe alone: therefore more than ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vigilant muſt the Saints be that are eſpouſed to Chriſt, to avoyd ſpirituall fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is<note n="(o)" place="margin">Si ſuſcepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri:, o homo, in cubili animae tuae adulterum diabolum, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retricata eſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima tua cum diabolo, ſi ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus irae, ſi invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diae, ſi ſuperbiae, ſi impudicitiae ingreſſus fuerit ad animam tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, &amp; receperis cum, &amp; conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeris ei loquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, &amp; in corde tuo delectatus fueris his, quae tibi ſecundum ſuam mentem ſuggerit, meretri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus es cum eo. <hi>Origen hom.</hi> 12. <hi>in Levit. c.</hi> 2. In nulla par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te oportet virginem adulteram eſſe, non lingua, non auribus, non oculo, non alio omnino ſenſu, imo neque cogitatione, ſed corpus quidem velut templum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quoddam aut thalamum ſponſi habeat praeparatum. <hi>Baſil. l. de vera virg.</hi>
               </note> committed when the ſoule proſtitutes it ſelfe to the leaſt ſinne, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaines the leaſt luſt with conſent and delight. If thou ſhalt receive, ſaith <hi>Origen,</hi> into the chamber of thy ſoule the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3510:59"/>
devill, thy ſoule hath played the adultereſſe with the devil, if the ſpirit of anger, envie, pride, immodeſtie, and the like ſhall enter into thy ſoule, and thou ſhalt entertaine and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto it, and be delighted with it and the ſuggeſtions thereof, thou haſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whoredome with it. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſoule may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſpirituall adultery with any ſinne, yet more hainouſly with theſe three particular ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, with<note n="(p)" place="margin">Idololatria eſt myſtica &amp; ſpiritualis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae cum idolis fornicatio. <hi>Com. a Lap. in</hi> Ezek. 6.9.</note> Idolatrie, for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> of this God profeſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a jealous God, <hi>Iſay</hi> 42.8. <hi>I am Iehovah and my glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will not I give to another;</hi> and of this doth the Lord often complaine that his people had gone a whoring after
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3510:60"/>
Idolls and ſtrange gods. <hi>Levit.</hi> 17.7. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9. Neither is there any one kinde of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fornication more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſtfull to the Brideſgroome of the ſoule, than for rhe ſoule to be difiled with this ſinne, therefore <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25. it is joyned with filthineſſe, <hi>from all your filthineſſe, and from all your Idolls, will I cleanſe you, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, with covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and inordinate<note n="(q)" place="margin">Mundi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor &amp; Dei, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter in tuo corde cohabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum iidem oculi coelum pariter &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram nequaquam aſpiciunt. <hi>Aug.</hi> (vel quiſquis eſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor) libro de duodecim abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionibus gradu. 7.</note> love of the world, this is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſinne with which the ſoule more hainouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits ſpirituall fornication: this the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, <hi>Iames</hi> 4.4. <hi>Ye adulterers and adultereſſes, know yee not that the friendſhip of the world is enmity with God?</hi> whoſoever
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3510:60"/>
therefore will bee a friend of the world is an enemie of God, this ſpirituall adultery with the world is ſo much more grievous than carnall adulterie; by how much God, who is contemned is more great and excellent than man to whom a wife hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>A third ſinne is corporall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> uncleanneſſe. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15. the Apoſtle ſhewes this, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that a man by this ſinne takes the members of Chriſt and makes them the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of an Harlot: this ſinne by Gods owne verdict takes away the heart. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.11. and ſo alienates the affection from the Lord Jeſus. Behold then the duty of the Saints, as to avoyd all ſin; ſo eſpecially
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3510:61"/>
theſe three ſinnes with which eſpecially and more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly, the ſoule commits ſpirituall fornication; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to preſent themſelves as chaſte<note n="(r)" place="margin">Virginitas mentis eſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegra fides, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida ſpes, ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra charitas, <hi>Aug.</hi> 11.13. <hi>in Iohan. Iom.</hi> 9.</note> virgines to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt their deareſt brideſgroome: This point in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs the Saints in a third duty to walke before Chriſt in al manner of well pleaſing; propounding Chriſts word and example as a patterne of their lives. This duty of a wife the <hi>Heathen</hi>
               <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ariſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Oeconom. c. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heſiod.</note> Philoſopher found out, affirming that a well ordered woman ought to eſteeme the carriage of her husband to be a Law of her life impoſed by God, though this rule faile in caſe the manners of the husband be ungodly and corrupt, yet in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3510:61"/>
the preſent inſtance betwixt Chriſt and his Spouſe it failes not, Chriſts life being a patterne of purity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect holineſſe and abſolute obedience in every particular: therefore ſaith<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                  <p>Nupſiſti Chriſto incede ſcoundum ſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi tui volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. <hi>Tertul.</hi> de velandis, <hi>virg. c.</hi> 16.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtianiſmus eſt invitatio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinae naturae. <hi>Nyſſen. tract. de profeſſ. Chryſtia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tertullian.</hi> Halt thou married thy ſelfe to Chriſt, walke according to the will of thy husband: this obſervancie and pleaſing car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was eminent in the Church. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.2. <hi>Behold as the eyes of ſervants looke unto the hand of their Maſter, and as the eyes of a mayden, unto the hand of her Miſtreſſe, even ſo our eyes waite upon the Lord our God.</hi> Chriſt would have his Spouſe to be knowne to bee his Spouſe, even by her out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward carriage, by her holineſſe towards God, and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3510:62"/>
towards man, by her meeke, humble, courteous and mercifull carriage towards al, expreſſing in her life, the life of her husband Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> In the ſecond place, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this point may be a ground of tryall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, whether a poore ſoule be eſpouſed to Chriſt or no: which it may doe by theſe ſeverall ſymptomes of this ſpirituall marriage.<note place="margin">1. Symptome.</note> A ſoule married to Chriſt is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected and grieved, for the want of the ſenſe of Chriſts preſence in the ſoule. <hi>Mat. 9.</hi>13. Our Saviour makes this an evident property of the Spouſe of Chriſt, that ſhee faſts and mournes at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the bridegroome. The Diſciples of <hi>Iohn</hi> asked
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3510:62"/>
Chriſt why they faſted, but his Diſciples faſted not, Chriſt ſeemes to tell them that they had reaſon to faſt and mourne becauſe their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was now in priſon, and they deprived of his preſence, but as yet his Diſciples en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the preſence of their Maſter, the delightfull reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their endeared Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome, but the time ſhould come that the caſe ſhould be altered, that I the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome of their ſoules ſhall be taken from them, and then they ſhould faſt and mourne, that being a fit time for deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſadneſſe of heart; now as it was with the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt in regard of Chriſts corporall preſence, ſo it is with every beleever in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3510:63"/>
regard of Chriſts ſpirituall preſence, they enjoyed for a while his corporall preſence, exceedingly rejoycing in the fruition of it, drinking in with great delight the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous words and ſaving do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that flowed from his bleſſed lippes, with great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, beholding his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious miracles which he did by his divine power, but when once this bleſſed bridegrome of their ſoules was taken from them, it was a day of much heavineſſe and ſadneſſe, of faſting and mourning; it is ſo with the beleeving ſoule in regard of Chriſts ſpirituall preſence, ſometimes Chriſt gives the ſoule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſenſible fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and apprehenſion of his ſweeteſt reſidence in it, at
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3510:63"/>
which time the ſoule takes a full draught of unſpeakeable and raviſhing joy, at other times Chriſt for ſome reaſons beſt knowne unto himſelfe, withdrawes himſelfe in regard of any ſenſe and feeling of his preſence by the ſoule: now at this time the ſoules former ſongs are turned into ſighes, its melodie into mourning, its feaſting into faſting, all its former joy for the preſence of Chriſt its Bridegroome, into ſaddeſt dejection for the withdrawing of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes preſence; hence it is that the Spouſe of Chriſt is ſo often in Scripture called a Dove, which is of a mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nature, when ſhee wants the Societie of her mate;<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14. Eſay 38.14. Eſay 58.11.</note> of the like carriage is Chriſts
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3510:64"/>
Spouſe in the abſence of Chriſt, ſee the Churches car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,<note place="margin">Cant. 3.1.2.3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ened.</note> 
               <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>By night on my bed I ſought him whom my ſoule loved, I ſought him, but I found him not. By night,</hi> that is, by ſolitary and deepeſt meditation, <hi>upon my bed,</hi> that is, when ſhee thought her ſelfe ſure of her beloved, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him to be with her, ſhe miſſeth his company, then ſhe by her meditation and prayer, falls a ſeeking of him but findes him not: doth ſhe not ſit ſtill as content to bee deprived of the preſence of her bridegroome? No, ſhee now reſolves to ariſe and to goe about the Citie and the ſtreetes, (noteing her diligent ſearch) to ſeeke him whom her ſoule loved, and yet ſhee
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3510:64"/>
findes him not, will ſhe yet leave off enquiring having loſt ſo much labour? No, ſhe reſolves upon a third enquiry after Chriſt of the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and keepers, to wit, of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and yet not finding Chriſt ſhe is yet impatient of Chriſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay and abſence, neither the ſociety of her brethren, or of Miniſters could comfort her troubled ſpirit for the want of Chriſt, and therefore ſhe ſtill perſiſts in her ſeeking till at laſt ſhee found him to her ſoules refreſhing: behold in this inſtance the true Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Spouſe of Chriſt, that ſhee is affected with the loſſe of his preſence, and will not be ſatisfied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fruition of it againe.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3510:65"/>
wouldſt thou then, O doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſoule, be aſſured that thou art eſpouſed to Chriſt: exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how thy heart ſtands affected for the want of the inward apprehenſion of Chriſts preſence in thy ſoule; if wanting Chriſts reſidence thou canſt be of a cheerefull heart, of a careleſſe minde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt, of a ſlow and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure carriage in ſeeking of him in his Word, Sacraments, or any other of his Ordinances, it is an evident ſigne as yet thou never enjoyeſt ſuch an husband as Chriſt, who after his eſpouſalls with the ſoule leaves ſuch an impreſſion of his love, and ſuch a liking of his preſence and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that let the ſoule bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived but a while of Chriſt, it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3510:65"/>
cannot reſt till it hath gotten him againe by the neareſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracings of Faith.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſymptome of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> this Spirituall marriage is this, as it may be diſcovered by the affection of ſorrow, as in the firſt place, ſo by the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of deſire. A ſoule married to Chriſt hath a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging deſire of full communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt in heaven; as a woman betroathed to an husband longs for the actuall and publicke ſolemniſing of her eſpouſalls, when ſhe may enjoy that familiar ſociety with him as to live in one houſe, eate at one table, ſleepe in one bed, and to bee unto him his boſome friend: it is ſo with Chriſts ſpouſe being once betrothed to him, ſhee
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3510:66"/>
deſires the conſummation of the marriage in heaven, where ſhe may reſt and repoſe her ſelfe, in a more neere commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, in the armes and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Jeſus Chriſt: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſoule bee betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed unto Chriſt upon earth, yet the fellowſhip is not ſo great, and communion ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate with Chriſt upon earth, as the ſoule ſhall have with Chriſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>Hence Saint<note n="(v)" place="margin">Iam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſata es illl, ô anima, jam nuptiarum prandium cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratur; nam cana quidem in caelo paratur. <hi>Born. Serm.</hi> 2. <hi>Dom.</hi> 1. <hi>poſt. Epiph.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> affirmes that in this life the marriage dinner is onely celebrated, but in heaven the marriage Supper is prepared, where the ſoule ſhall be fed with rarer dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and be ſatisfied even to a ſpirituall inebriation, with
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3510:66"/>
the fulneſſe of Gods houſe. In this life, whilſt the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age dinner is only celebrated, there may be want of wine, as at the Marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> Chriſt himſelfe being preſent, but not at the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſupper in heaven, though in <hi>Cana</hi> yet not in <hi>Canaan</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</p>
            <p>At the Marriage in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> although the mother of Jeſus told him of the want of wine,<note place="margin">Iohn 2.4. ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> that hee might ſee the ſcarcity ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet Chriſt anſwered her, his <hi>houre was not yet come,</hi> that is, the convenient time of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Miracle was not yet come; but when the Maſter of the Feaſt and Bridegroome began to be aſhamed of their ſcarcity, and that the Miracle
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3510:67"/>
might the better be taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, then Chriſt gave him plenty enough. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in this life, whilſt the marriage dinner laſts, there may be want of wine, that is, want of the ſenſe of Chriſts preſence, his favour and love, and therefore the Spouſe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Stay me with flaggons,</hi> and the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the houre is not yet come when Chriſt uſeth to give the ſoule ſuch plenty, but he reſerves that plenty for heaven, when he fills the ſoule with the wine of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable pleaſure and joy in his preſence, when hee will turne all the waters of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, into the wine of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and the ſoule ſhall have acceſſe to Chriſt, the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3510:67"/>
fountaine of all comforts, there to fill and ſatisfie it ſelfe with what the heart is capable of, there being then a more intimate communion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Chriſt and a beleever in heaven, than upon earth, a more intimate fellowſhip and a fuller participation of that unſpeakeable content that the ſoule takes in Chriſt; the ſoule cannot but<note n="(w)" place="margin">Quemad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus magna cum alacritate mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravit in Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ut ibi vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret gloriam Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephi. Gen. 45.18. ſic nos ad caelum propere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ut ibi vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus gloriam Chriſti <hi>Chem. Harm. Evang. p.</hi> 1679.</note> long for and deſire with <hi>Paul</hi> to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and to be with Chriſt: with <hi>Iacob</hi> it cannot but waite for the Salvation of God: with <hi>Simeon</hi> it cannot but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to depart in peace, where it may ſee Chriſt face to face, and never loſe that beatificall viſion of him againe. Hence was it that good<note n="(x)" place="margin">Quid hic faciemus? cur non ocyus mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramus? cur non hinc avolamus?</note> 
               <hi>Monica</hi> the mother of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3510:68"/>
what doe we here? why depart we not ſwifter? why flye we not away from hence? Hence was it that her ſonne<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mori deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dero ut videam Chriſtum ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare meum: vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere renuo ut cum Chriſto vivam. <hi>Chem. ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Evang. p.</hi> 1675.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayd, I deſire to dye, that I may ſee Chriſt my Saviour, I refuſe to live, that I may live with Chriſt. It is with a beleeving ſoule in this life, as with a man in a journey in a ſtrange Country, who though at his Inne, where he lodgeth, he hath a warme Chamber, good fire, whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome victualls, a ſoft and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing bed, yet he is ever and then thinking on home, his thoughts and meditations e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and then ſpeaking thus within him: true it is, I have a good lodging, kinde enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, wholeſome victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, but what are all theſe to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3510:68"/>
my fare at home, my bed at home, to the ſociety of my wife and children at home, home though homely is ever in his minde, ever in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: ſo it is with a Chriſtian eſpouſed to Chriſt, though he enjoyes a confluence of all outward comforts, though hee takes great delight in this life, and as it were ſwimmes in all worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments; having a loving wife, dutifull children, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants, his barnes ſtuft with graine, his paſtures ſtockt abundantly with Oxen and ſheepe, his coffers reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of metalls, ſo that hee lackes nothing that can give an honeſt heart content, yet he cannot but bee ever and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3510:69"/>
then thinking within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, I have wife, children, lands, livings, but what are theſe to the ſociety with my ſweeteſt Saviour, and moſt delightfull Bridegroome; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to leave all to bee with Chriſt which is beſt of all. Examine thy heart, O ſoule, by this property. Is there any thing in the world ſo deare unto thee, be it wiſe, ſonne or daughter, land or houſe, yea life it ſelfe, that thou art not content to leave, that thou mayſt have that intimate communion with Chriſt in heaven? Thou mayſt juſtly feare thou never waſt eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Chriſt, neither ever hadſt any acquaintance with him, for if thou hadſt, the beſt of worldly excellencies
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3510:69"/>
could not retaine thy ſoule from a deſire to bee with Chriſt in heaven.</p>
            <p>In the third place,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Symptome.</hi>
               </note> this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall marriage is diſcovered by the affection of love.<note n="(z)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Auſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Oeconom. c. ultima.</note> A ſoule married to Chriſt loveth all that have any alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with Chriſt. A wife that truely loves her husband, loves her husbands kindred and friends, in like manner are the friends of Chriſt deare unto his Spouſe: now who they be that have alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and friendſhip with him Chriſt himſelfe declares. Firſt, that thoſe are his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>Marke</hi> 3.35. who doe the will of God, whoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his Father, whoſe God is his God; and for his friends Chriſt ſhewes who they be,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3510:70"/>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.14. <hi>Ye are my friends if ye doe whatſoever I command you:</hi> as it was betwixt <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> and <hi>Ahab.</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 3.7. when they agreed together to goe againſt <hi>Moab</hi> to battell, <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> ſayd, <hi>I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horſes as thy horſes,</hi> ſo is it with all the members of Chriſt that are eſpouſed to him. Chriſts cauſe is their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cauſe; Chriſts friends their friends, embracing Chriſt with the deareſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and mutually one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for Chriſts ſake. By this mayeſt thou examine thy ſelf whether thou beeſt eſpouſed to Chriſt or not, to wit, by thy love to all thoſe that ſtand in the ſame relation to Chriſt as thou doſt: ſeeſt thou a
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3510:70"/>
poore member of Chriſt, in the wrinckles of whoſe face, as in ſo many lines, thou mayeſt read Lectures of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and want; here is a friend of Chriſt, if thou beeſt the Spouſe of Chriſt, thou canſt not but have ſome pitty, love, and compaſſion on this his friend, ſeeſt thou any eminent for grace, holy in life, frequent in duty, zealous for piety and purity of heart, this is a friend of Chriſt, ſtanding in the ſame relation to Chriſt, as thou doeſt, if thou beeſt eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſed to him, and therefore thou canſt not but love him for the image of Chriſt thou ſeeſt in him.</p>
            <p>In the third place, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> of this point ſerves for conſolation to Chriſts
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3510:71"/>
Spouſe in many particulars. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt againſt the clamour of the guilt of ſinne. Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an husband to the Soule undertakes all its debts: the Widdow of the Prophet. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.1.2. complaines that the Creditour was come to take her ſonnes captives; but the Spouſe of Chriſt needes feare no ſuch arreſt of any creditour, the ſoule hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny creditours that out of Chriſt it is ſubject and lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſatisfie: the Law ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts the ſoule, with a <hi>curſed is every one that continueth not in all things that are written in the Law to doe them, Gal.</hi> 3.10. Againe Conſcience arreſts the ſoule and ſeconds the Law with this aſſumption, that the ſoule hath not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3510:71"/>
continued in the Law but broken it: the Devill will ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the ſoule with many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations; Death and Hell have their arreſts too, but Chriſt being the husband of the ſoule, becomes the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaker for all theſe arreſts and debts by ſinne, Sathan, Conſcience, Death, or Hell; when the Law ſhall urge its <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and rigorous exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of perfect obedience, then may the beleeving ſoule anſwere, my husband Chriſt hath payd it for me: when the Law calls for penalty up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the violation of it ſelfe, the beleever may anſwere, Chriſt my husband hath payd it for me, who is made unto me <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſnes, ſanctification, and redemption,</hi> &amp; as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:3510:72"/>
ſpeakes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a ranſome, but a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-ranſome for all my ſinnes, and thus in all other arreſts may the ſoule ſtop all in Chriſt: ſo that as good <hi>Oneſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was loath to returne to his Maſter <hi>Philemon,</hi> to whom once he had beene an unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſervant, but when once he knew that <hi>Paul</hi> had written his Epiſtle to <hi>Philemon,</hi> to tell him that whatſoever <hi>Oneſimus</hi> owed him he ſhould ſet it on <hi>Pauls</hi> ſcore,<note place="margin">Philem. v. 18.</note> 
               <hi>Oneſimus</hi> might then with boldneſſe returne to his Maſter <hi>Philemon</hi> againe: in like manner a poore ſoule conſidering how it hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended God, is loath to come before or into his preſence: but when it conſiders againe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3510:72"/>
that whatſoever it is indeb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God it is ſet on Chriſts ſcore, then may the ſoule with boldneſſe goe to God, and ſtop the mouth of all accuſers in the world, who can lay nothing to the charge of Gods elect, ſeeing it is God that juſtifieth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ſoule againſt the feare of ſpirituall enemies, the wife that hath a rich and powerfull husband, thinkes her ſelfe ſafe from reproaches, injuries, and abuſes of others: farre more ſafe is the ſoule that is married to Chriſt, from being hurt by the attempt of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or by any aſſaults of any ſpirituall adverſaries, for Chriſt is able to vindicate the cauſe of his oppreſſed Spouſe
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3510:73"/>
to the utmoſt. Protection is one priviledge the wife hath by her husband, therefore ſaith <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Boaz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 3.9. ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> 
               <hi>Spread thy skirt over thine handmaide, for thou art a neere kinſman: Spread thy skirt over me,</hi> that is, be my protector in being my hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; Chriſt will not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his Spouſe in any comfort or ſuccour that a wife expects from her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, much leſſe in protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, one of the meaneſt duties of a loving husband, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. when once the time was, the time of love betwixt the Lord and his people, he ſaith, he ſpread his skirt over his people, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their nakedneſſe; let then the Spouſe of Chriſt be dayly aſſaulted by Sathan,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:3510:73"/>
the world, and the remainder of corruption, and let the ſoule goe to Chriſt, as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Boaz, Spread thy skirt over thy ſervant,</hi> for thou art my husband, Lord, and Maſter, and the Spouſe of Chriſt ſhall be ſafe under the wings of Chriſt, that all the powers of darkeneſſe, and powers of hell it ſelfe, ſhall not be able to pull Chriſts Spouſe out of his Armes.</p>
            <p>This may comfort the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving ſoule, that being once eſpouſed it ſhall be for ever eſpouſed to Chriſt, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19. <hi>I will betroth thee unto my ſelfe for ever,</hi> ſaith the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his people.<note place="margin">Ruth. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Naomi</hi> may be deprived of her husband <hi>Elimelech</hi> in a ſtrange land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Elimelech</hi> was a man ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:3510:74"/>
to the like mortality as all of his owne ſpecies are, but the ſoule once married to Chriſt can never bee deprived of him, who being both God and man, is he who was, and is, and ſhall be unto all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſo that which <hi>Babylon</hi> ſayd in a proud and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous manner, <hi>Eſay</hi> 47.8. <hi>I ſhall not ſee widdow-hood,</hi> that upon good grounds and not preſumptuouſly may the ſoule eſpouſed to Chriſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme of it ſelfe: I ſhall ſit as Queene and never ſuffer ſpirituall Widdow-hood, ſo that the condition of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in this marriage eſtate with Chriſt, is farre better than that of <hi>Adam</hi> in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. Man in his innocencie was eſpouſed to God, but
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:3510:74"/>
then God left in man a power to diſſolve this matrimoniall knot, and man breaking the Covenant there was a dvorce drawne, now God is ſo farre pleaſed out of his ſuper-abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant mercy and compaſſion (not to be found in any but a God infinitely good) to treat of a ſecond marriage to the ſoule of man divorced from him,<note place="margin">Ier. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> which marriage is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon a more ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion even upon Chriſt, and in Chriſt he is pleaſed to bee married to the ſoule, not for a certaine time to be at laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired, but for all eternitie, not now leaving the Matrimoniall covenants in mans own cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, but undertaking the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of them himſelfe. To conclude this, if it be ſuch an
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3510:75"/>
happie thing for man and wife ſo to live together,<note n="(a)" place="margin">Faelices ter &amp; amplius quos irrupta tenet copula, nec ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis divulſus que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimoniis ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma citiùs ſolvit a nor dic. <hi>Hor.</hi>
               </note> that the bond of love be not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken till death it ſelfe doth breake it, then farre greater happineſſe and comfort for a beleeving ſoule to thinke, that this bond of Spirituall wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke ſhall not be broken by death it ſelfe, but remaine indiſſolveable to all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> In the fourth place this point ſerves for exhortation. It may be a ground of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion to every one that is as yet an aliant from <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a ſtranger from God, from his promiſes, his Chriſt, that he would accept of Jeſus Chriſt to be the husband of his ſoule, and ſo his ſoule may be the Spouſe of Chriſt, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:3510:75"/>
ſo have intereſt in all the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſes of the Goſpell, and be made a member of the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and of one that was a farre off made nigh to God in Chriſt by Spirituall alliance. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.29. the Baptiſt ſtiles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a friend of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Paul,</hi> as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or ſpokeſman of Chriſt, tells the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that he was jealous over them, for he had eſpouſed them to one husband that he might preſent them as a chaſte virgin to Chriſt. Every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpell with the Baptiſt ſhould be a friend of the Bridegoome, with <hi>Paul</hi> a ſpokeſman for Chriſt, this the Apoſtle ſheweth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. that he and the reſt of his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:3510:76"/>
function were Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though Chriſt did entreate others by them to be reconciled to him; for as great perſons, as Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Kings, dwelling in remote places from the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Ladies whom they would eſpouſe unto themſelves, ſend entreaties of marriage by their Ambaſſadors, who uſe to carry their lively pictures and portratures of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſo preſent them to the women they deſire to be eſpouſed unto: in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Lord Jeſus the great King, whoſe Throne endureth for ever, and whoſe Scepter is a right Scepter, keeping his Court in heaven and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his glorious Throne where his chiefe reſidence is,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3510:76"/>
and his greateſt glory diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he offering conditions of Marriage to poore ſoules, ſends them by the Miniſters of the Goſpell his Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors, and hath put into their hands the word of his Goſpell (Chriſts love Letter) in which his glorious excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies and treaſures of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable benefits, dwelling in him in a plentifull manner are evidently ſet forth, which the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt opening and declaring to the people, cannot but ſhew forth the excellencies of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of his riches, honour, beauty, and all other deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualities in a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome. Oh then that God would be pleaſed (having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed me an unworthy
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:3510:77"/>
meſſenger to this great digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as to be his ſpokeſman) to make me an inſtrument of perſwading ſome poore, blind, and naked ſoules to accept of Chriſt to be their husband, who is able to inrich them with what their ſoules can deſire, and now what argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall I uſe to perſwade ſuch to this Marriage?<note place="margin">Gen. 24.35.36.</note> 
               <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> ſervant going to take a wife for his Maſters ſonne <hi>Iſaac</hi> that he might perſwade <hi>Rebecca</hi> and her friends the more forceably, the one to goe with him, and the other to part with her, he tells them that <hi>the Lord had bleſsed his Maſter Abraham greatly, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo by this Argument ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines his requeſt in perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Rebecca</hi> to goe with him,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:3510:77"/>
and her friends to part with her. The great God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven imploying mee his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervant to intreate a Spouſe for his ſonne, I can uſe the ſame arguments that <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant did, I wiſh it might be with the ſame ſucceſſe. My Maſter the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> is exceeding great (his greatneſſe being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſſe) and he is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding rich, not onely with <hi>Abraham</hi> in flockes and heardes, in ſilver and gold, the cattle upon a thouſand Mountaines being his,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.12.</note> but he is the poſſeſſour of heaven and earth it ſelfe, the great Commander and Soveraigne Lord of the whole world, rich in himſelfe, unſpeakeable,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:3510:78"/>
incomprehenſible and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable glorious eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and this God hath one onely begotten ſon, and unto him hath he given all his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, as in the 2 <hi>Pſalme,</hi> and the 8. <hi>verſe. Aske of me and I will give thee the uttermoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion;</hi> the ſonne of God inſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into his Fathers inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances offers himſelfe to bee married to thy poore ſoule, whoſoever thou art, that wilt accept of him to bee thy Bridegroome: Oh that thy ſoule with <hi>Rebecca</hi> would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of this match without farther delay! The<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. Ethic. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher tells us that ſometimes a lover findes fault that he loves above meaſure, and yet is not loved againe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:3510:78"/>
he hath nothing in him that is amiable or worthy of love. Chriſt indeede may complaine that he offers love to many a poore ſoule, and yet findes no love againe; neither can the ſoule alleadge this for a reaſon of unkinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Chriſt againe, that there is nothing in Chriſt that is lovely; for in Chriſt there is nothing that is not worthy of the greateſt love that can lodge in a mortall breaſt: what lovely quality can the ſoule deſire in an hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, that are not in Chriſt? Doth the ſoule deſire riches? <hi>With me are riches, Prov.</hi> 8.18. ſaith Wiſedome it ſelfe. Doth it deſire Nobility of Birth? God the Father wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes his ſonnes Nobility.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:3510:79"/>
               <hi>Thou art my Sonne, this day have I begotten thee, Pſal.</hi> 2.7. Doth it deſire beauty? <hi>Chriſt is fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer than the Sonnes of men, Pſal.</hi> 45.2. Deſires the ſoule pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in an husband for prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? <hi>All power is given unto him of the Father,</hi> twelve Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Angels are at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and Legions of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills were conſtrained to crouch unto him; hence alſo by the Prophet was he called <hi>Wonderfull and Powerfull, Eſay</hi> 9.6. Deſires the ſoule goodneſſe in an husband? Chriſts <hi>lippes are full of grace, Pſal.</hi> 45.2. He is a very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of goodneſſe. Deſires it yet Wiſedome? Chriſt is Wiſedome it ſelfe, <hi>Wiſedome of the Father, and made Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to every beleever,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:3510:79"/>
Laſtly, deſires it glory in an husband? Chriſt is the <hi>King of glory, Pſal.</hi> 24.8.10. The Apoſtle remarkeable ſets downe all theſe amiably qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities together, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.3. <hi>God hath in theſe laſt dayes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken unto us by his Sonne,</hi> behold his Nobility, <hi>whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed heire of all things,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his Riches, <hi>by whom alſo he made the world,</hi> behold his Wiſedome, <hi>who being the brightneſſe of his Fathers glory, and expreſſe Image of his Perſon,</hi> there is his beauty <hi>and uphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all things by the Word of his Power, when he had by himſelfe purged our ſinnes,</hi> there is his goodneſſe, <hi>ſate downe at the right hand of the Majeſtie on high,</hi> there is his glory. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over all theſe excellencies are
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:3510:80"/>
in Chriſt, ſo they are in him in a more<note n="(c)" place="margin">Neceſſario efficitur in Deo omnium rerum in eſſe perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, eaſque perfectiſſimas perfectiſſimo modo. <hi>Zan. de natura Dei. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. Many excellencies may be in the creatures by partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation from God, but they are not ſo in the creatures as in Chriſt: many excellencies are ſprinkled up and downe in the Creatures, in an imperfect manner, as ſome creatures excell in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſome in power, ſome in wiſedome, but all theſe and many more that are diverſe and oppoſite perfections and vertues in the Creatures, are al in Chriſt in a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and eminent manner: there is as the Apoſtle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes <hi>One manner of glory in the Sunne, another of the Moone, another of the Starres;</hi> yet what glory the Moone hath
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:3510:80"/>
or the ſtarres, they receive it for the moſt part from the Sunne, and all their glory meetes in the Sunne in a full manner: ſo it is with the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in heaven, as of Angels and Saints, another of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures under the heaven, yet what glory is found in theſe creatures they have it from God, and Chriſt the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe; and meetes in him as in a center of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, making one perfect ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and excellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And now O humane ſoule, what is there in the world in which thou canſt finde theſe things that are to be found in Chriſt? why doſt thou then wed thy heart to riches, honour, pleaſure, that<note n="(d)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern. ſerm. in iliud.</hi> Ecce nos reliquimus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. Anima, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, rationalis caeteris omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus occupari poteſt, repleri non poteſt. Anima ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis facta eſt capax majeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis tuae, ut a te ſolo, &amp; a nullo alio poſſit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleri, <hi>Aug. in Soliloq. c.</hi> 30.</note> cannot ſatisfie thy
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:3510:81"/>
ſoule, and ſlighteſt Chriſt in whom are treaſures of riches, ſupercoeleſtiall honour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceiveable pleaſures? Why doeſt thou give Chriſt the loweſt place in thy heart, that deſerves the higheſt? Why putteſt thou the creature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Creator, who at the firſt gave thee dominion over the creature? What ſhall I ſay to perſwade thee to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all other lovers, to give entertainement to Chriſt, that he may eſpouſe himſelfe to thy ſoule? I cannot ſpeake more impreſſively than in the words of the<note n="(e)" place="margin">Quid per multa vagaris, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omuncio quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo bona ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae tur &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris tui? Ama unum bonum in quo ſunt omnia bona, &amp; ſufficit: deſidera ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex bonum, quod eſt omne bonum &amp; ſatis eſt. <hi>Aug. vel quiſquu eſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. l. de Spit. &amp; Anima.</hi>
               </note> Father. Why doeſt thou, O man, wander up and downe by many things, by ſeeking the good of thy ſoule and body? Love that one God in which are all
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:3510:81"/>
good things, and it ſufficeth: deſire that one good which is every good, and it is enough. And now me thinkes I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome ſoule, with <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa, almoſt perſwaded to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> to accept of Chriſts of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and willing to match with him, but yet fearing and ſecretly ſaying within it ſelfe, I am afraide that Jeſus Chriſt will not match himſelfe with me, who have nothing in mee that may move Chriſt to love me, and I finde ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in my ſoule by ſinne, ſo much filthineſſe in my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, that Chriſt, I feare, will turne away his eyes from me, as an unfit object of his love. To this I anſwere, what ſaw God in his people that might move him to love
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:3510:82"/>
them. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.5.6. <hi>They lay tumbling in their blood, in their filthineſſe, and abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and then was the time of love when God pittied them, and entred into covenant with them, and they became his owne.</hi> It is not with Chriſt as with a man, in chooſing a Spouſe: man lookes after proportion and portion: but Chriſt regards not the ſoule for any thing in it ſelfe, for he hath riches and beauty enough for himſelfe, and the ſoule his Spouſe too: If the ſoule hath any riches or righteouſneſſe of its owne, Chriſt will not marry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe unto it, and therefore the Apoſtle affirmes that the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> going about to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh their owne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, did not ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3510:82"/>
to the righteouſneſſe of God, <hi>which is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt layd hold on by faith, Rom.</hi> 10.3.4. As therefore <hi>Abraham</hi> ſayd, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.23. unto the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> that <hi>he would not take from him ſo much as a thread, leſt the King of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhould ſay, I have made A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham rich:</hi> ſo Chriſt, when he Marries himſelfe to any ſoule, he will not have with it the leaſt righteouſneſſe of his owne, leſt the ſoule ſhould boaſt of it ſelfe, or that it had any riches but what it got by its Marriage with Chriſt. Therefore in that thou ſayeſt thou art poore, baſe, blinde, naked, miſerable, and wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and if withall thou art truely ſenſible of this thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, thy filthineſſe and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:3510:83"/>
wretchedneſſe, touched alſo with a deepe apprehenſion of thine own unworthines to be joyned in Marriage to Chriſt, thou haſt ſpoke a word ere thou wert aware, that may give thee comfort and hope, that thou art ſuch a one to whom Chriſt will eſpouſe himſelfe: wert thou rich in thine owne conceite as the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Non habet quo intret gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, ubi meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum occupavit. <hi>Bern. in Cantie. Serm.</hi> 67.</note> Chriſt would deſpiſe thee, but being vile in thine owne eyes he will ſooner regard thee, who uſeth <hi>to fill the hungry with good things, and to ſend the rich emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty away: to reſiſt the proud, but to give grace to the humble:</hi> there is nothing that winnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect more from God, than for the ſoule to bee truely humble. <hi>To him will I looke,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:3510:83"/>
even to him that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſaiah. 57.15.</note> 
               <hi>I dwell in the humble heart,</hi> though God dwells in the higheſt heavens, yet withall in the loweſt heart, and therefore ſaith <hi>Mary: Luk.</hi> 1.48. <hi>He had reſpect to the low eſtate of his hand-maide.</hi> Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is the expreſſion of Holy<note n="(g)" place="margin">Altus eſt Deus, humilis eſt Chriſtianus. Si vult ut altus Deus v. cine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur illi, ille humilis ſit, magna myſteria, fratres, Deus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per omnia eſt. Erigris te &amp; non illum tangis, humilias te, &amp; ipſe ad te de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendit. <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 34.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to this purpoſe, God is high, (ſaith he) a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is low, if he deſires that the high God ſhould come neare him, let him be lowly. A great myſtery: brethren (ſaith he) God is above all; thou lifteſt up thy ſelf and yet toucheſt him not, thou hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt thy ſelfe, and he deſcends unto thee: ſo then as <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gails</hi> ſpeech to <hi>David</hi> deſiring Marriage of her, that ſhe was not worthy to waſh the feete
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:3510:84"/>
of <hi>Davids</hi> ſervants; allayed not <hi>Davids</hi> affection, neither hindred her preferment; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will thy poverty (if thou beeſt truly ſenſible of it) hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy eſpouſing to Chriſt, who, as the<note n="(h)" place="margin">Nullum eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git dignum ſed eligendo efficit dignum. <hi>Aug. cont. Iuli. Pelag. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> Father notes, chooſeth none worthy of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but by chooſing them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the worthy. To conclud this: it was a good policie in the <hi>Gibeonites, Ioſh.</hi> 9.4, 5, 6. that they might move <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to enter into covenant with them, they workt wittily, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king old ſackes upon their Aſſes, and wine bottles old and rent, old ſhooes and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It would be as good a policie for a poore ſoule in moving Chriſt to enter into league and covenant with it, to come unto Chriſt with an
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:3510:84"/>
abaſed, naked and ragged heart, rent in peeces with deepe contrition, and ſenſe of Gods wrath, for this is the moſt ready way, for the ſoule to finde favour in the eyes of Chriſt, whoſe order is firſt to deject, then to erect and raiſe up, firſt to wound by the ſenſe of miſery, and then to heale by the ſenſe of Mercy: firſt to make the ſoule apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of its owne miſery and then to beſtow himſelfe upon the ſoule to enrich it.</p>
            <p>But in the ſecond place ſome poore ſoule may object:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>2</label> I am content to be married to Chriſt, but loath I am to part with ſuch a ſinne that affords me ſo much honour, credit, dignity, and riches.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwere: he that
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:3510:85"/>
truely accepts of Chriſt, muſt take him on his own tearmes, to be the Lord and chiefe Commander of his ſoule, and the ſoule muſt give a bill of divorcement to every ſinne, to give entertainement to Chriſt alone, whereas then the ſoule pretends a willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to accept of Chriſt, and yet withall an unwillingneſſe to part with ſome darling ſinne, the reaſon is becauſe the ſoule conſults with fleſh and blood, with corrupt nature, that alwayes (as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſayd of <hi>Michaiah</hi> in another caſe) propheſieth evill to the ſoule, oppoſing it ſelfe againſt the eternall welfare thereof. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of me, ſaith Chriſt, to be the Bridegroome of thy ſoule, the ſoule askes counſell
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:3510:85"/>
of fleſh and blood, whether it ſhould obey in accepting of Chriſt: refuſe ſaith fleſh and blood, wilt thou forſake thy former delights, thy <hi>Dalilahs,</hi> in whoſe lap thou haſt tooke ſo many a contentfull ſleepe, wilt thou forſake ſuch a way of gaine, which hath beene the maintenance of thy ſelfe and family? Hereupon the ſoule reſolves upon a plaine deniall, or if not ſo, yet of an accepting, but not on his owne termes, yet Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede ſhall be called the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of the ſoule, but withall reſolves to retaine its ſinnes ſtill, which in truth is aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to a plaine refuſall; would the ſoule then accept of Chriſt in his owne way, the beſt direction that can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:3510:86"/>
to the ſoule in ſuch a caſe is, that it ſhould not conſult with fleſh and blood and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature in this caſe, but to doe as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. Who upon Gods call and the Revelation of his Sonne, in him immediately obeyed, and <hi>conſulted not with fleſh and blood.</hi> The<note n="(i)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eter. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> Philoſopher tells us, it is abſurd to conſult about things that muſt bee done of neceſſitie: now there is nothing of greater neceſſity than for the ſoule to accept of Chriſt: doth Chriſt then offer himſelfe unto thee, reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an immediate embracing of his love. Doth hee bid thee forſake thy ſinnes for him, delay not the buſineſſe, conſultation and delay in this caſe is dangerous, we muſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:3510:86"/>
fight againſt our affections, ſaith<note n="(k)" place="margin">Contra af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus non ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate ſed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petu pugnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt.</note> 
               <hi>Seneca,</hi> not by ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of argument, but by force and violence. Our Saviours counſell is good to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>If thy right eye cauſe thee to offend pull it out: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pull it out,</hi> not pick it out, as the Eagle of the vallies doth the eye of her prey by degrees, but pull it out altogether: ſo <hi>if thy right hand cauſe thee to offend, cut it off,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5.29. &amp; 30. opened.</note> in the originall it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies in the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis of the word, <hi>chop it off,</hi> not ſaw it off by degrees, but <hi>chop it off,</hi> that is on a ſudden, cut it off on a ſudden, cut off thy ſins that are as deare as thy right hand. Would the ſoule then reſolve upon a divorce of ſinne for Chriſt, and upon a peremptory will to roote out
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:3510:87"/>
all ſinne, let it lend no eare to Sathan, or corruption to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade and counſell the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but on a ſudden to ſet upon the worke, and to part with all ſinne, and thy worke might be done with leſſer difficulty. It is with the ſoule in this buſineſſe of parting with ſinne for Chriſt, as it is with a boy tenderly bred, that goes to bath himſelfe in the River: who if he enters in at ſome ſhallow place, and wades deeper and deeper by degrees, hee ever and then ſhrinkes backe, and is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to goe no further, being impatient of the coldneſſe of the water, at the length out he goes againe, and leapes into the water, and on a ſudden hee wets his whole body, and
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:3510:87"/>
then he feeles no cold. A ſoule in like manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves to leave its ſinnes, and to accept of Chriſt, it begins to leave this ſinne and that ſinne, it findes this to be harſh to its corrupt nature to part with theſe beloved darlings, upon this it beginnes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with its owne deceitfull and corrupt ſelfe, whether it ſhould goe on or no; corrupt nature diſſwads, upon this the ſoule returnes to its old ſinnes againe: the beſt way for the ſoule ſuddenly to part with all ſinne, even with the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of ſinne, reſolving ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the power of an Almighty God, never to commit the leaſt ſinne wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly or willingly any more, and the ſoule being win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:3510:88"/>
up to this firme reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and keeping it ſelfe ſo by the power of Gods ſpirit aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, the divorce of ſinne will not be ſo grievous, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory leſſe difficult, for when the ſoule once hath parted with all ſinne to accept of Chriſt; it ſhall finde that ſweeteneſſe in one houre by Chriſts preſence, that a world of earthly and carnall delights cannot afford in many yeares. Oh then let not the ſecret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in any baſe and ſordid luſt keepe thee, O ſoule, from the right enjoying of thy ſweeteſt Saviour; part with all thy ſins in exchange for this precious pearle, and I will aſſure thee this, that although the parting with thy ſinnes may ſeeme grievous to thee
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:3510:88"/>
for the preſent; as the death of <hi>Abſalon</hi> was to <hi>David,</hi> yet as he loſt but a rebellious ſonne, ſo doſt thou loſe but a treacherous enemie to thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall good:<note place="margin">Gen. 21.12.</note> therefore as God ſayd to <hi>Abraham</hi> concerning the parting with <hi>Hagar</hi> and her ſonne; <hi>Let not the thing bee grievous unto thee:</hi> no more let this parting with thy ſinnes trouble thee, for thou ſhalt inſtead of carnall baſe and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall delight in the enjoying of ſinne, have an inconceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able delight in the enjoying of Ieſus Chriſt, the husband of thy ſoule, a ſippe of which pleaſure to be found in Chriſt will aſſwage the deſire of the beſt of carnall delights. For as Chriſt ſaith concerning the new wine and the old,<note place="margin">Luke 5.23,</note> the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:3510:89"/>
contrary may be ſayd of this new condition of being Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to Chriſt, and the old of being in the ſtate of nature. <hi>No man having taſted the Old wine,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>cares for the New, for the old is better than the New:</hi> ſo no true Chriſtian that hath got into this new condition, deſires the old a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; none that hath taſted this new wine of pleaſure and joy to be found in Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to drink of the old wine of fleſhly and wordly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights againe: heare the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of<note n="(l)" place="margin">Illud revera ſolum eſt gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium quod de creatore conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur, cui com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parata omnis aliundèjucundi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tas maetor eſt, omne dulce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum eſt.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard,</hi> that is onely true joy that is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God, to which all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mirth being compared is but ſorrow, all other ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, griefe and bitterneſſe. Aske holy<note n="(m)" place="margin">Pota me domine tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis caeleſtis, ut nil jam munda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum libeat deguſtare vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natae dulcedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:3510:89"/>
he is of the ſame opinion, for thus he prayes unto God, <hi>Lord give me to drinke of the brooke of heavenly pleaſure, that I may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taſte any more of the poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſweeteneſſe of worldly things:</hi> Aske <hi>David</hi> he is of the ſame minde, <hi>One day in thy Courts is better than a thouſand.</hi> Laſt of all, let Chriſt himſelfe be wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who affirmes that it was his meate and drinke to doe <hi>the Will of his Father in heaven,</hi> ſhewing thereby that what pleaſure and delight it is to be hungry and thirſty, to be refreſhed with wholeſome food, the ſame delight it was to him, and is to all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to walke in the wayes of God, and in obedience to his Commandements enjoying thereby the peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:3510:90"/>
in aſſurance of Gods love which is a continuall feaſt, and now, O reſolute ſoule for Chriſt, art thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to accept of Chriſt for thy husband upon his owne termes, to be the ſole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of thy heart, art thou content to be ſubject to him in all his Commands, be they in doing, or in ſuffering; I will be thy Prophet: Chriſt Jeſus will meete thee and embrace thee for his Spouſe, hee will cloath and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne thee with the needle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of divers colours, even with the variety of graces, and when the Lord Jeſus, the endeared Bridegroome of thy ſoule, ſhall come at the Laſt Day, he will account of thee as a wiſe Virgin ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:3510:90"/>
the Oyle of Grace in thy Lampe, and thou ſhalt enter into the Bridegroomes Chamber, there to reſt in his Armes and boſome unto all Eternity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:91"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3510:91"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
